<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The third part of the soul's delight collected and composed out of the works of the glorious virgin, St. Teresa of Iesus (author of the reformation of the Holy Order of the B.V. Mary of the Mount Carmell,) by the R.F. Paul of St. Vbald, religious of the same order, for the comfort of those that are more spirituall, and haue supernaurall prayer.</title>
            <title>Jesus Maria Joseph Teresia. The soul's delight.</title>
            <author>Teresa, of Avila, Saint, 1515-1582.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56724</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P876B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218976</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830520</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830520</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34972</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56724)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34972)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2109:04b)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The third part of the soul's delight collected and composed out of the works of the glorious virgin, St. Teresa of Iesus (author of the reformation of the Holy Order of the B.V. Mary of the Mount Carmell,) by the R.F. Paul of St. Vbald, religious of the same order, for the comfort of those that are more spirituall, and haue supernaurall prayer.</title>
                  <title>Jesus Maria Joseph Teresia. The soul's delight.</title>
                  <author>Teresa, of Avila, Saint, 1515-1582.</author>
                  <author>Paul, of St. Ubald, Brother.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>112, [8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by William Lesteens in Hoochstrat at the signe of the Pellican,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>In Antwarp :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an index.</note>
                  <note>Bound after Wing (2nd ed.) P876A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the Trininty College Library, Cambridge.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34972:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34972:1"/>
            <p>THE THIRD PART OF THE SOVL'S DELIGHT, Collected and compoſed out of the workes of the GLORIOVS VIRGIN, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. TERESA OF IESVS (Author of the reformation of the Holy Order of the B. V. MARY of the MOVNT CARMELL,) BY THE R. F. PAVL OF S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. VBALD, RELIGIOVS OF THE SAME ORDER, For the comfort of thoſe that are more ſpirituall, and haue ſupernaturall Prayer.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Sine intermiſſione. Orate</hi> Pray without intermiſſion. <bibl>1. Theſal. 5. v. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meditatio cordis mei, in conſpectu tuo ſemper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The meditation of my heart, is allwayes in thy ſight;</p> 
               <bibl>pſal. 18. v. 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>IN ANTWARP By WILLIAM LESTEENS in Hoochſtrat at the ſigne of the Pellican. 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:34972:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:34972:2"/>
            <head>THE THIRD PART Of the ſoul's delight, wherein is treated of ſupernaturall prayer, and ſeuerall degrees thereof.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>THE FIRST CHAPTER. A briefe relation of ſupernaturall Prayer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr Holy Mother S. Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſa in her life, and her other woorkes, doth declare, and explicat this matter ſo well, that I neede not ſpeake much of it. But by reaſon her workes, or bookes cannot be had by euery one, I will briefly ſay ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of it, out of her, for the comfort, of pious ſoules, and to encourrage many to goe forward, in this Bleſſed exerciſe of mentall prayer, ſeing, to what great hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe they may attaine, by it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the better vnderſtanding of what is to be ſayd, you muſt obſerue, that as there are vertues, which we call, acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; by reaſon they are gayned by our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, induſtry, and practiſe; there be alſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34972:3"/>
vertues which we call infuſed, that is; not gained by our induſtry, or labour, but are giuen vs, by the meere gift of God, which are certaine habits, of vertues, that doth cauſe vs promptly, and with facility to vſe and produce vertuous acts. theſe are infuſed into the ſoul, she not knowing how, but that she finds by the effects, that it is a ſpeciall gift of God, which is ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, perceiued, and to which, she could not attaine, with the labour of many yeares.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In like manner, there is prayer, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, or naturall; and infuſed, or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall; that naturall, is gayned by the long practiſe of it, as we get other artes, or trades, by the dayly vſe of them; but this infuſed, is in an inſtant giuen vnto vs, by God, and it doth cauſe vs, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in a more perfect manner, and more knowingly, and more feelingly, we not knowing whence, or how it came; and therefore it is called ſupernaturall, being beyond our reach; but ſometyme this prayer is giuen only for that preſent and perhaps, at other tymes; yet it is not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall, becauſe it is not permanent, though ſupernaturall, and this doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce great, and good effects in the ſoul; but the other, cometh with a preſence of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34972:3"/>
God, ſo perfect, that going to prayer (though you were in diuerſe occaſions of buſineſſe, inſtantly before; which we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſufficient to diſtract a man a whole day) ſuddenly ſet on your knees in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, with a looke on that preſence of God, you are recollected and haue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient matter, to employ the powers in, ſo that the ſoul, is in a great content, with the inward ſatisfaction, which she doth feele; and this is not without contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and though the naturall contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, delighteth the mynd, and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſoul much; yet this other, giueth more content and ſatisfaction in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, then that is euer able to reach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, with all induſtry poſſible;</p>
               <p n="4">4. This is commonly giuen only to ſoules that are pure, and after long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour (in the practiſe of the other prayer, mortification, of their ſenſes, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; and pennance for their ſinns;) are wery of the world; and doe loath the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nityes, and pleaſures thereof; and doe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to the loue of God, and true, perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. theſe ſoules doe now deſire ſolitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, and doe betake themſelues from all occaſions, into the moſt ſecret places, they can find, fit for their purpoſe; to gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue themſelues to holy reading, prayer,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:34972:4"/>
and other ſpirituall exerciſes, as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſaints, did, into the wilderneſſe, ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and deſart places, to be employed, and familiar with God alone.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For theſe places are moſt fit for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection, and contemplation; and the ſpirit of God, hath this property, that it deſireth to be in priuat, employed only in heauenly things, and ſuch as are eternall. and this doubtleſſe, was the cauſe, that in former tymes when there were more ſaints, in the Church, then now; the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bayes, and monaſteryes, were built in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote and ſolitary places, farre from the noyſe, of people; where all things, and euen the very ſolitude moſt, did moue, and inuite them to recollection, and contemplation of diuine matters;</p>
               <p n="6">6. For euery creature there, doth teach vs to know our ſelues, our creatour, and his perfections. for there, we shall ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the heauens ouer vs, the earth vnder, the water ebbing, and flowing, going and coming, the trees, hearbs, and flowers, now ſpringing, then faire, ſoone after, withering, decaying, and fading away; the beaſts feeding, and bellowing, the byrds flying, and ſinging; all of them, in their kind manifeſting and praiſing their common Lord the creatour of all things,</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34972:4"/>
7. The earth when we looke downe, telleth vs, that we are duſt, from it; and muſt returne to it againe, be we neuer ſo powerfull, or great; this, dayly experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce doth confirme. the water and its cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, shewes the vncertainty, mutability and vnconſtancy of the life, of man, and his vaine deſyres. the trees, flowers, and the reſt, doth shew, how long a man is coming to perfection, and on a ſudden is gon by death; the beaſtes tell vs, with all others, that we are not, of our ſelues, but haue a God, (who gaue vs our being) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit wiſe, and prouident, preſeruing, and prouiding for all, in their owne kind; when we looke vpwards, we ſee the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and they tell vs, that there, is the place and ſeat, of all felicity, and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, where God and his Angells, in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry are reſident, and that we are created, to enioy God there; and therefore ought to tend thither, and labour to compaſſe it, by ſeruing and praiſing him, who hath ſo created vs, and prouided for vs, as to be with himſelfe in all ioy, and glory, for all eternity; this good, and much more, ſolitude affordeth, in thoſe deſart places, the ſoul then that is deſirous of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and therefore doth retyre her ſelfe from occaſions, and in that ſolitude doth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34972:5"/>
giue her ſelfe to more reading, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to come to the more perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg and feeling of God, that she may loue and ſerue him, in a better, and more eminent way, then euer before, muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue to ſeeke after God alone, all other things whatſoeuer neglected, and forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; which the great God of mercy, and goodneſſe obſeruing; and ſeing how that poore ſoul, doth labour in prayer with her vnderſtanding, and will, to find him by loue; and is often tyred, vſing great diligence heerein; at length taketh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion vppon her, and eleuating her, ſpirit, doth ſet her at reſt, with great ſweetneſſe, in a deepe recollection, farre, within her ſelfe, in a ſolitude, of an other kind; where she enioyeth ſo perfect a feeling of his preſence within her ſelfe; that she could neuer haue imagined, it; which ſetleth all the powers in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and giueth her admirable content, and inward ſatisfaction, farre ſurpaſſing what she Felt before. This ſolitude wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thin <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo. cap.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 10. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; chap</hi> 6. <hi>v</hi> 19. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</note> her ſelfe, is the kingdome, and liuing temple, of God, and the ſeat of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall wiſdome; the manner of going thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as is ſaid', is by an inward recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, introuerſion, or rather attraction of the powers, and ſenſes, ſo ſtrongly,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34972:5"/>
and ſuddenly, that the ſoul is in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to ſee ſo ſudden an alteration, but how, or what it is, she knoweth not, but she doth plainly perceiue, that she is ſo well employed, and her happines ſo great, that she would not be thence though she could, for all this world.</p>
               <p n="8">8. This recollection, is farre different from that other, which we procure; of which I ſpoake formerly; for that doth conſiſt in this, that we doe ſeriouſly by ſome pious conſideration apply the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers to the preſence of God, which we doe conceiue, or frame inwardly, which giueth great content, and cauſeth them eaſily forget outward things; yet the ſoul cannot but feele the powers working, with the noyſe of words, and know that they are, in their owne proper home, and that by their induſtry, that recollection is procured; but this othet is not procured, but ſuddenly giuen them, and they are more deeply recollected, and in a greater ſolitude, ſo farre within the ſoul, that they admire, how they came thither; and they woorke ſo ſlowly and attentiuely that they doe neere forget, both houſe, and home, with the preſent content. ſo that the one, is had, with labour, and difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the other is giuen them, with eaſe, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34972:6"/>
ſweetneſſe. the one is acquired, or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, this other infuſed, and ſupernaturall, farre ſurpaſſing our capacity, and reach; more inward, with greater light, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſatisfaction, and a deeper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of truthes, in the ſoul; for it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from a more noble of spring and begining, which is God himſelfe; alſo it leaueth, and diſpoſeth the ſoul richly, and well, for higher matters; ſo that, in the firſt, we worke, in our ſelues, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collection<hi>:</hi> in this other, we are the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and God worketh it in vs; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſayd by his Holy Prophet, I will <note place="margin">
                     <hi>O ſee.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</note> lead her into the ſolitude or wilderneſſe, and there I will ſpeake vnto her heart, he doth not ſay, that she will goe, but I will bring her thither; to shew, that the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, is his, and a gift, that the ſoul with all her labour, and induſtry, could neuer reach vnto, or compaſſe; that she might be the more gratefull;</p>
               <p n="9">9. But you muſt vnderſtand, that as by degrees, we acquire morrall vertues, or the perfection of naturall prayer, ſo by degrees, or certaine ſteps, (as we may ſay,) God leadeth his beloued ſpouſe, into this ſolitude, and Paradiſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and firſt he giueth her a continuall preſence of him ſelfe, which is ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:34972:6"/>
with ſo efficatious and feeling a knowledg, that she cannot but certainly belieue that he is there within her, yet she perhaps taketh no notice of it, to know what it is, but the light is great, and the effects of his preſence, are very euident, this is not an imaginary preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, but a light that bringeth a Maieſty with it, which (with one looke on it) procureth in the ſoul, moſt profound hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and an admirable reuerentiall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect towards his diuine Maieſty, out of which aſpect, and reſpect; there follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth a ſweet content, and many delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full teares; ſo that when the ſoul pleaſe, she may looke in, and preſently find with whom to conuerſe, without any labour; and ſufficient matter to keepe her em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployd; and this is the firſt ſtep, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree;</p>
               <p n="10">10. The ſecond ſtep wherein he lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth her forward, is, that recollection, of which I ſpoake laſt; for the ioy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent which proceedeth from that contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall aſpect, inſtantly recollecteth all the powers, though they were neuer ſo much diſtracted before, and giueth them ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious employment, that they eaſily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all outward obiects, attending only, to what is there; which bringeth the ſoul
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34972:7"/>
to haue great freedome, hauing nothing to diuert her intention, nor attention; out of that recollection, and ſerious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, the light, and affection doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, at which the powers, are in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and ſilence. (and this is the third degree) expecting to ſee what will be the concluſion; for Heere the ſoul ſeemeth truly to haue found whom she loued, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note> and ſought for; and now doth hold him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and will not let him goe, as is ſaid in the canticle; they are heere preſent to gether, very euidently, and feelingly, there is no noyſe of words inwardly, but by affection, and loue they are vnited forcibly, reſting ſweetly in the bed of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light; and the very powers haue ſo great content and ſatisfaction, that they would not haue the very body, to moue or breath, leaſt (as our Holy Mother ſayth) <note place="margin">In her life chap. 15.</note> ſo great a good should be loſt, or ſcape out of her hands; as if by that meanes she could keepe it, being the gift of God, depending only of his diuine will, and pleaſure; who giueth it when, to whom, and for as long tyme as he thinks fitting, and it can be no longer; heere the ſoul truly feeleth how great the power of God is, and how ſweet he is to thoſe that loue him</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:34972:7"/>
11. Hence his diuine Maieſty leadeth her forward into the depth of the inward ſolitude, that is, to a higher and more eminent degree of prayer, where she may more perfectly, and fully enioy his preſence, and receiue greater bleſſings, then in the former; this is called the ſleepe of the powers, for in the former, they all were in great ſilence; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is called quiet prayer, or the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer of reſt, by reaſon all the powers the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re doe reſt from their operations or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing, are quiet, and in ſilence; out of which, the ſoul falling more deepely in loue, the delight and inward ioy increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, ſo, as the powers are in a manner ouercome, and are begining to looſe them ſelues by degrees; as one ſlumbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and falling a ſleepe, that know's not what he doth, or where he is; this ſoul is like to one that lyeth a dijng, his forces failing by degrees, vntill he grow ſo weake, and feeble, that he has ſcarſe any ſenſe, or feeling of any thing, knoweth, no body, nor where he is, nor what he doth, or is done to him; yet is not dead, but betwixt both, as we may ſay; our Holy Mother compareth the ſoul in this degree, to one who is gon ſo farre into a <note place="margin">In her life chap. 16.</note> deepe water, that it reacheth to the chin;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34972:8"/>
goe forward, he cannot; neither doth he know, how to turne back; neither would he, though he could, and thus she betwixt both, begins in a manner to ſink and fall a dijng; for the waters of delight are now in ſuch a height, that the powers are ouercome, and the ſoul looſing her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and the vſe of her powers, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, is like to yeald the Ghoſt; and thus with loue and exceſſe of ioy, both she, and all the powers, are not themſelues, but ſopited, and like to one (as is ſaid) wholy ſenſleſſe; and the ioy, and content, which is heere had, by farre exceedeth that of the former degree; yet his diuine maieſty, (with this not contented) to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his loue the more to this his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſpouſe, he bringeth her into a ſolitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, beyond all that is created, (and this is the fourth ſtep, or degree, called vnion) where all are abſorpt and drowned, ouer head, and eares; for she and all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, are wholy vnited to God, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulfed in the depth of his diuinity, and she is become one and the ſame with God, quite forgetting all that is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and earth, and the very body, which during the tyme of vnion, is voyde of ſenſe, and in a manner dead, neither doth she know whether she be in the body or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34972:8"/>
no. in this vnion, she doth not continew long, (perhaps halfe an hour, or there about) before ſome of the powers doe returne to them ſelues, and often, not fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the like content, (as one should ſay) in their owne houſe, they goe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly back againe, and are drowned in the ſame depth, and burned with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me fire; and in this coming, and going, ſome houres, may be ſpent; but not in the totall, or perfect vnion of all; for as our Holy Mother ſaith, it is ſo ſtrong and forcible that our weake nature is not able to endure it long; but by degrees his diuine Maieſty doth enable the ſoul, and make her capable for receiuing thoſe ſupernaturall fauours, and diuine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications;</p>
               <p n="12">12. In this totall vnion, the ſoul kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth nothing as is ſaid, but enioyeth a content and happineſſe, ſurpaſſing ſenſe; yet, what she doth enioy; or how; she vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth not; but doth remaine ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorpt, and vnited to the diuine eſſence; and thus she is become God's captiue, tyed and chayned faſt, by loue; and hath no power, to free her ſelfe, vntill his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, be pleaſed to ſet her at liberty; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would she, though she could, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it a greater captiuity, to be left to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34972:9"/>
her owne liberty, and farre more liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be in that ſweet and happy capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity; this is a greater and more eminent gift, and fauour, then all the former, it is a moſt bleſſed vnion, or coniunction; a moſt diuine transformation; a moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py death; a true deification; and moſt happy life in God.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Note, that in that quiet prayer, the will only is vnited, and not the other po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers; in that other of the ſleepe of the powers, the will and the powers are vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but ſo, that they are not perfectly vnited, or wholy loſt; but in this vnion, they are all wholy and perfectly loſt vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and in gulfed in the diuine eſſence, and they are wholy dead, to all the world, drowned in vnſpeakable delight; and the profit of the ſoul in this degree, is vnexplicable; her loue is come to ſo great a height, that nothing, but the enioying of God wholy and perfectly, can giue her content; Therefore his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſty doth lead her to an other ſtep, or degree, farre beyond her ſelfe, and all that hath beene ſayd; eleuating her ſpirit, and opening her eyes, to ſet and know, ſomwhat of his greatneſſe, and the treaſure of his celeſtiall glory, with viſions and reuelations of high
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34972:9"/>
matters, hidden and moſt profund miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes; and this is called and exſtaſy, or rapt, where she vnderſtands cleerly, and plainly, how all things created, are a meere shadow, and nothing, compared with what she then doth enioy, and ſee in God; and this rapt, ſome tymes, is ſo forcible, and vehement, that it doth ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat the very body with the ſoul from the earth, and remayneth hanging in the ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and it doth ſo participat of the inward ioy, and glory of the ſoul, that it doth loath, to be longer on earth, and faine would be inueſted with immortality, for all eternity; and after theſe great raptes, commonly when the ſoul returneth to her ſelfe, the body as yet, and perhaps for ſome dayes, will not be able to vſe its owne functions; nor the powers, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, are themſelues, but all are out of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for they are as yet drunk, with the memory of the glory, and delight, which they enioyed; and the introuerſion, and application of the powers and ſenſes, is ſo great, that they cannot but with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, attend as yet to any outward things; and though they ſee and heare at thoſe tymes, yet they neither well ſee, nor know what they ſee, or heare; this ſoul now is no more her owne, but wholy
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34972:10"/>
belongeth to God; for she hath conſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her ſelfe, her will, and the keyes the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rof, vnto his diuine Maieſty. ſo that she liueth not now, but Chriſt doth liue in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</note> her; in ſo much, that she myndeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but the honour, glory, and praiſe, of God: and heartely deſireth, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth, that all may loue, and praiſe him for euer: her vertues, are ſolid, and of great perfection; her loue is ſo exceſsiue, that her life on earth, is a continuall martyrdome, and death; by reaſon of her forcible and languishing deſyre, to be diſſolued, and be with her beloued, Chriſt Ieſus in glory for all Eternity.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Thus deere Chriſtian ſoul, our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour doth reward, euen in this mortall, and myſerable lyfe, the litle labour, and endeauours, of a louing ſoul; O who would not labour, for ſo great a good? and willingly ſerue ſo good a Lord; O who would not affect ſo true a louer, and deere a frend? o who would not freely forſake all this world, for the loue of ſo bountifull and Gracious a God? O Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Lord, prayſed and exalted for euer, and euer mayſt thou be, who art ſo choy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of vs, and ha'ſt prepared ſo great hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſse for ſuch wormes of the earth, as we; all thy creatures, loue, and praiſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:34972:10"/>
thee, for euer more. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>THE II. CHAPTER. Of Recollection, and quiet Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, more in particular.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHereas this recollection, is ſo great, and inward; and the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers not troubled, with the noyſe of worldly, and vaine thoughts; and that God is there preſent, what muſt the ſoul doe in this recollection? firſt she muſt conſider that he is there only attending to giue audience, and ready then to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re her petition, and that she can without any impediment ſpeake to him, being ſo neere (for as our Holy Mother ſayth, the <note place="margin">In her life chap. 27.</note> ſoul ſeemes to haue other, eares, and ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue inwardly, and needeth not, ſpeak loud, or cry out, with noyſe of inward words, or conſider him in heauen, or a farre of or without her ſelfe, to be heard, or vnderſtood; but she may reſt there with him (for he is not a frend of many words) and accuſtome the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to worke very ſlowly, and as it we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in ſilence, carefully attending to what is ſaid, and with what reuerence, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34972:11"/>
confidence, she ſpeaketh to him: and if the vnderſtanding can be kept quiet, ſweetly beholding that preſence, of his diuine Maieſty, without words, or with <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> the Publican caſting his eyes, to the earth, expecting with humility, what shall be ſayd to him, it will be of great profit; and increaſe vertuous deſyres in the ſoul; contempt of the world, and ſtrong reſolutions, to ſerue God, and amend their liues; and this the ſoul doth vnderſtand by ſweet inſpirations, and ſecret whiſpers, by which he ſpeaketh vnto her; heere she doth offer her ſelfe, and her will, wholy to God, to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed euer after, in his ſeruice;</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though ſome, (yea religious) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter coming ſo farre, and hauing forſaken the world, and giuen themſelues to God, doe returne back to the flesh pots of Egipt, and as a dog to his vomit, to be more worldly then euer, and to ſeeke for familiarityes, and frendships; and they take back againe, from God (euen againſt his will,) what formerly they freely gaue him (THEIR VVILL) which they did dedicat vnto his diuine <note place="margin">Note.</note> Maieſty; to be employed only, in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice; which againe they diſpoſe of, as of their owne, and the world and what is in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34972:11"/>
it, which for his ſake they forſooke, they ſeeke after, more earneſtly, then before they left it; and thus they draw their mynd, and affection from God, applijng them ſelues, to baſe, vile, and tranſitory things; notwithſtanding the experience, they often had, by many comforts, and conſolations, of Gods goodneſſe, and loue, when they did proceede ſincer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And one thing may be much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired; to wit, that theſe vngratfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, do goe to prayer, as boldly, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout all feare, as if they had done no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, to God, nor wronged themſelues; and they are not ashamed, to aske, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſpirituall comforts, and fauours of his diuine Maieſty, after ſo great an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front: are theſe to be regarded, or fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red more by God? certainly, they deſerue it not; vnleſſe with a humble ſubmiſſion, and acknowledgment, of their abuſe, and wrong committed, they returne to his Maieſty, forſaking all, and reſtoring what was vniuſty taken away, without which, this recollection is not had agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, for it doth conſiſt in this, that the powers are introuerted, and not troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with any vaine or worldly thoughts. as is formerly ſaid. But they who goe on,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34972:12"/>
with their endeauours, to pleaſe God; doe eaſily find how ſweet, and good, our Lord is, to thoſe that loue, and doe ſeeke after him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is a comfortable thing, to ſpeake of the next degree (to which they are brought after that recollection) and of what paſſeth there; and ſeriouſly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, is moſt ioyfull, and pleaſing; but to feele it, is in exceſſe delightfull; this is in Quiet Prayer, where the ſoul is placed to reſt without labouring or diſcourſe; heere she is feaſted with varietyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly comforts, diuine conſolations, and ioyfull delights, farre ſurpaſſing ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe; heere she doth begin to taſte of the food of Angells, and is repoſed in the bed of ſweet content; certainly, if all the honours, paſtines, and pleaſures of this world, were in one, and to continue, and be enioyed for euer, yet compared with one only moment of the ioy, content, and ſatisfaction, which heere are had, all that would appeere to be meere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; for as farre as the heauens, doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the earth, in greatneſſe, and perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, without any proportion; ſo doe theſe ſpirituall comforts, without any equality, or proportion, exceede all the others; words cannot expreſſe, what it
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34972:12"/>
is; but thoſe happy ſoules can beſt tell, and declare it, that by experience hath often knowen and felt the ſweetneſſe of it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. This Quiet prayer doth conſiſt in this, that the ſoul and all the powers, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter labouring to find out whom she doth deerely loue, are brought by his diuine Maieſty, from that laborious diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and ſearching for him; to the place of reſt, that is farre within her ſelfe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, in great ſilence, and peace of all the powers, she doth enioy his preſence, and is vnited to him ſtrongly by loue, and doth remaine in his ſweet embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with great content, and ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and this is therefore called quiet prayer, by reaſon, there is no diſcourſing nor noyſe of inward wordes vſed, in it, where with, the ſoul, and powers, were often weryed, ſearching to find him; but all are ſilent, and quiet; not that they doe omit to worke, but it is ſo ſweetly done, that it is ſcarcely perceiued, by reaſon they are in contemplation, and with one ſimple looke, they are in admiration with great ioy, and doe feelingly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, more in an inſtant, then they could attaine to, with all the diſcourſes poſſible; let not any thinke that the ſoul
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34972:13"/>
doth ſee any image, or shape wherein God doth appeere when his preſence is named heere, but only that she hath a fixt memory with a liuly faith that he is there, and that by the effects, which she doth find in her ſelfe it appeeres; as a great ioy and inward ſatasfaction of all the powers. Alſo a light which procureth a moſt humble and reuerentiall reſpect in the ſoul with a kind of certainty of his preſence, with which, she is ſo contented &amp; delighted, as if nothing more reſted to be deſyred in this world<hi>:</hi> and this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent doth redowne euen to the body which is neuer wery whiles that quit content doth hold;</p>
               <p n="6">6. And obſerue, that as it is former<hi>'s</hi> ſaid, the will being only vnited, the other powers, which are not ſo, doe keepe he often in warre, and doe moleſt her much endeauouring to bring her from her reſt, and content, to paſſe the tyme, (as we may ſay) with themſelues, but their labour is in vaine, and the contrary doth often happen. for she doth cauſe them to returne to their quiet reſt with her, for she doth labour to keepe in, that litle ſpark of fire, of the loue of God, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it (as of right she ought) of great worth; for thence (if she be not in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34972:13"/>
fault,) in tyme may proceede a great fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and flames of diuine loue; for she doth now by experience well know, how great good it is, to adheare to God, who gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th that ſmall begining, as a liuly token of his affection, and earneſt penny, to bind the bargaine, and confirme the agreement, betwixt them; to wit; that she muſt not be longer of this world, though liuing in it; but of thoſe, whoſe conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, is in heauen; and diſpoſe her ſelfe, for greater, and higher matters; and to be diſpoſed of, only by his diuine Maieſty; who hath now choſen her to be of his priuat chamber, and to ſeeke after no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what shall be to his honour and glory; O admirable dignity and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe?</p>
               <p n="7">7. Let not any ſoul that is come to this ſtate, vnderualue her ſelfe, nor think it want of humility, to conceiue that she is fauoured, by God; for one will be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re thankfull, that he knoweth the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the gift, or benefit, and dignity of the perſon that giueth it, then if they did not marke it, or did forget it; or would not acknowledg it, but she muſt with an humble ſubmiſſion, and holy preſumption acknowledg that she is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, without any merit, on her part;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34972:14"/>
and that it is the meere goodneſſe, and mercy, of his diuine Maieſty that will haue it to be ſo; that she may know how much she is obliged, and returne a ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re affection, anſwerable to his intention and not fruſtrat him, of his expectation; for certainly this will encourage her, to goe forward, dayly in Gods ſeruice, and to vndertake greatter matters, for his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, honour, and glory; and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue it, that a ſoul truly humble. cannot haue a greater confuſion, then to ſee her ſelfe fauoured, and honoured, without any deſert or merits; and well knowing her owne demerits; which cauſeth her, to be more humble, and thankfull; and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous, to pleaſe him more then formerly; for this truth is imprinted in her, ſo fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, that she cannot but ſee, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it; ſo that in the preſence of that Maieſty, which she knoweth to be ſo great, and powerfull, she would euen an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nihilat her ſelfe, if that she could; for she is not ignorant, of her owne nothing, and vnworthyneſſe;</p>
               <p n="8">8. But ſome ſoules, doe thinke their tyme loſt in prayer, and without profit, when they doe not diſcourſe, but are in that ſolitude, ſilence, and quietneſſe, not knowing what they doe, or ought to doe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34972:14"/>
in that caſe; but they are miſtaken; it is not ſo; as they themſelues, both then, and after, doe perceiue, by the effects, which they find in themſelues; for firſt they find an alteration, and ſweet content in them ſelues, they perceiue a great ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in all their powers, with ſo great ſuanity, that it doth redowne to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and ſenſes; in ſo much, that at that ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, it would grieue them, to be moleſted, called vppon, or ſpoaken to; nay they would not moue, nor ſtirre, nor breath, leaſt to hinder their ſweet repoſe, and ioyfull reſt in God; and after prayer, there remayneth ſuch a memory, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, of his preſence, in the ſoul, that she cannot in a very long tyme forget him, and this quietneſſe is ſo pleaſing, with ſo great humility, and feeling, that if they were called to dinner, or ſupper, their griefe is not litle, and I haue ſeene the teares run downe the cheekes of ſome as they did eat; lamenting that they were forced to leaue that celeſtiall banquet, with their Soueraigne Lord, and only good; to feede and feaſt, a corruptible body, their greateſt enemy, and cauſe of their moſt hurt, and euil.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But let them not be troubled, that they doe not diſcourſe, nor knowe what
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34972:15"/>
they doe; and only reſt in that ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, with God, for he teacheth them in an inſtant as is ſaid, more, then what with the diſcourſes, of all their life, they whould be able to reach vnto: therefore our Holy Mother doth aduiſe to ſtay in that ſilent quietneſſe without noyſe of inward words, enioying that ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent attending to nothing elſe; for now she is in poſſeſſion of what she ſought for; ſo that all her diſcourſe, is now in vaine, and to noe other purpoſe, then to trouble her in her ioy and reſt. Yet if her quietneſſe, and feruour be declyning, or decaying; it will doe well, to make ſome amorous act which may blow the coale, and keepe in the fire of diuine loue, leaſt it should decay, and perish; but this act muſt be made ſlowly, and attentiuely, with great ſweetnes, for if you vſe any force to increaſſe the ſeruour of your ſpirit, it is no other, then to caſt water to ſmother and extinguish that litle fire, of deuotion, which is as yet burning; for this being a ſupernaturall gift, and his worke, you muſt with humility giue his diuine Maieſty way, to doe in you, and with you, what he thinketh ſitting; and it is his worke, to increaſe it, or diminish it; for it is beyond our reach; and therefore
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34972:15"/>
in vaine we labour, to attempt that which ſurpaſſeth our ability, and exceedeth our forces; and if the vnderſtanding shall ſeeme to bring reaſons to moue the ſoul to more ſorrow, or gratitude, let not the ſoul permit it, nor regard it; but keepe the vnderſtanding as quiet as she can, without troubling her ſelfe; and if she cannot ſo doe, let her keepe her ſelfe in her reſt, and content; and not mynd, what the vnderſtanding doth in that; but leaue him of, to himſelfe;</p>
               <p n="10">10. You muſt alſo note, that as I ſayd formerly, she muſt not be deſyrous of guſts, and conſolations; but content her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, with all indifferency, in what shall be done by his diuine Maieſty, and be as <note place="margin">Guſts and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations muſt not be deſired in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, nor affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, for it she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes litle humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> ready, to help our Sauiour, to carry his croſſe; that is, to ſuffer aridityes, tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and contradictions, as to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted at his table, with delights, and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations; for truly; the more we deſyre, and ſeeke after theſe guſts, and comforts, the leſſe we shall haue of them, and the leſſe mortified, and perfect we shall be; for it is a great want of humility, as I ſaid elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; and for that preſumption, and want of humility, the ſoul is depriued, of what comforts, she had; and often doth remaine in great aridity. Therefore we
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34972:16"/>
muſt allwayes humble our ſelues, and acknowledg our ſelues, vnworthy of any fauours from his diuine Maieſty, whom we offended; and with plaine ſimplicity, offer our deſyre, and ſome reſolution, or purpoſe, to doe ſomewhat, though neuer ſo litle to content, and pleaſe him; with which he is more pleaſed, then with all the learned diſcourſes, eloquent words, and pregnant reaſons, which can be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him.</p>
               <p n="11">11. And when the ſoul is in that quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and ſo neere to his diuine Maieſty and after that she is now familiar and ſatisfyed with great ioy, and content, is the beſt and only tyme, to pray, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the neceſſityes of the Holy Church, the ſoules of Purgatory, the conuerſion of ſinners, our parents, frends and benefactours, and other neceſſityes to his diuine Maieſty; not by noyſe of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, but by an affection, and feeling de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre, that his Maieſty will be pleaſed, to grant, what is deſyred; for it is no more then to haue theſe in your mynd, and with a ſimple looke, to preſent them to him, for he doth well vnderſtand the leaſt of our deſyres, and that ſimple me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall, with a ſincere affection, doth preuaile more with him, then all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorick
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34972:16"/>
of the world; and if the recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or quietnes be great, the ſoul can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without much trouble, either produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce or attend to any inward framed words; Alſo it would diuert her attention from the better, and principall obiect: as if one looking with content on a ſweet pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, should heare a noyſe behind him, and should turne about to ſee where, and what that noyſe is; would not he be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted from that content; which he had in beholding the picture? doubtles he would; it is the ſame in this; for if the ſoul that is ſeriouſly applyed, and ioyed in God, should looke back and attend to the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and noyſe of the words, inwardly pronounced, by this attention, she would be diuerted from that ſweet content, which she had in God; therefore woords of diſcourſe muſt be omitted, or that content loſt.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Our Holy Mother doth declare in <note place="margin">In the caſtle of the ſoul. manſ. 4.</note> a good manner the difference betwixt the comforts, and conſolations, which proceede from our diſcourſe, and that which his Maieſty giueth, without our labour; comparing them to water, which in two wayes, or manners doth water a garden, the one is brought from a farre of, with labour, and through conducts;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34972:17"/>
or gutters, and falling into ſome ſiſterne is diſtributed, or caſt heere and there to water the garden, this is like the noyſe, and labour of the vnderſtanding, that with many reaſons, and diſcourſes, doth moue the will, to ſome pious affection, wherin she is comforted and delighted: but the other is neere hand, and at home, increaſing allwayes, in ſilence, and not perceiued, whence it cometh, but the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterne is ſeene full, and runing ouer, which watereth the garden better, more plentifully, and without the labour of the gardener, by reaſon the ſpring is in the bottome of the ſiſterne, whence wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout noyſe, the water doth iſſue. euen ſo, the guſts, and comforts, had in quiet pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, doe proceede from the euer liuing ſpring, that great God, of glory, and all conſolation; who is in the center of the ſoul, and without any induſtry or labour on our part, doth fill vp the ſiſterne of our heart with vnſpeakable ioy, whence not knowing how, the water of comfort, ouerflowing, in ſilence runneth to all partes of the garden, that is, to all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, ſenſes, and the very body it ſelfe, watering, and delighting all; and they admire, whence that ſo great content should be, which they doe feele; and in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34972:17"/>
this ſweet content and delightfull admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration they doe reſt. the other water doth penetrat but litle, in compariſon of this; for this doth enter into the very depth and inward ſubſtance of the ſoul; and leaueth her ſatisfied for a long tyme, by reaſon it is more plentifull, and in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abundance.</p>
               <p n="13">13. And this is the benefit of an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoul, for as water remaine's not on the tops of hills, or mountaynes, but fall's into the lowe places, and valleys; ſo <note place="margin">The good of a hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoul.</note> the water of comforts, and the grace of God, cannot ſtay vppon the hills, or mountaynes of proud and preſumptuous ſpirits, but doe fall into the valley of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, which is the humble heart, that thinketh lowly of it ſelfe; for he doth loue to be with the humble, and vppon them his Holy Spirit doth reſt, and to them he giueth his grace, and beſtoweth ſuch fauours vppon them, that with the great content, and inward ioy which they feele, the powers, and ſenſes are ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended. when he is ſo pleaſed; and the waters of delight, doe ſo recreat. and comfort both ſoul, and body, that ſome being ſick going to prayer, and brought to this quietneſſe, are not only during the tyme of that prayer, ſenſleſſe of any
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34972:18"/>
ſickneſſe, but after prayer, are voyde of all paine, and in good health; and many going to it with ſore heades, after that prayer, are very well; and this is a kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen thing by experience;</p>
               <p n="14">14. So that this prayer, leaueth great effects in body, and ſoul; for beſyde what is ſaid aboue, it dilateth the heart, and maketh the ſoul, more capable of diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne fauours, and free from ſeruile feare, worldly affections, and proper intereſt, she now doth take delight in doing of pennances, she regardeth not commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or health; ſo she may but pleaſe and ſerue God in any thing; her faith is more liuly, her deſyre to ſuffer perſecutions, and wrongs, for loue of him, increaſeth; she doth more feare to offend God, then all the torments and deuils, of hell; by reaſon she doth now loue him, whom she doth then perceiue to be truly loue, and praiſe worthy, by all creatures, for his owne goodneſſe, and perfections; and therefore she doth vnderſtand, that it is an vnworthy thing, to offend ſo high a Maieſty, in the leaſt thing: which doth cauſe her to keepe a pure conſcience, as neere as she can; her hope, and confiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, in his diuine Maieſty, and deſyre to enioy him in glory for euer, is greater,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34972:18"/>
and more conſtant, then formerly. and thus are the labours of a louing ſoul well recompenſed.</p>
               <p n="15">15. O how highly then ought we to eſteeme this benefit? and deſyre to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe him, who hath ſo great a care of vs; O my deere Ieſu, the true louer of humble ſoules, why are there not many more, that by this way of prayer, doe ſeeke after thee, to partake of theſe diuine benefits, and celeſtiall communications, ſince thou art ſo good, ſo liberall, and willing to enrich all, with theſe and many more heauenly bleſſings and fauours? our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mother ſayes that the reaſon of it, is, <note place="margin">In her life chap. 11.</note> that we doe not diſpoſe our ſelues, as we ought, and put on a ſtrong reſolution to forſake all things at once, and our ſelues chiefly; but doe reſerue ſome intereſt, or other, that we ought for his pure loue, vtterly to mortify, and forſake; though we eſteeme them, but ſmall matters: which really are of great importance, though it were, but our affection, to our parents, or frends; or perhaps; they doe not belieue what is written of theſe things; by reaſon they ſeeme to them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; and that what is ſayd of theſe rare matters, is but a flowrish of faire and ſweet words, and no reall truth; but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34972:19"/>
my God, thou do'ſt well know, that they are reall deedes, and therefore, the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoules, that goe on in thy ſeruice by this way of prayer, thou do'ſt often ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke wonderfull to the world, in their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and workes; which others doe not take to heart, nor conſider a right. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore I beſeech thy diuine Maieſty, to giue all that shall read this booke, and follow this path of prayer, a true feeling of what is heere ſaid; for then they shall ſee, and know this truth, and how farre short, all words, and expreſſions, are, to what really, and ioyfully is had in this bleſſed exerciſe of prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>THE III. CHAPTER. Of the ſleepe of the Powers.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IN the former degree, you haue ſeene what quiet prayer is, and how ſweetly the ſoul is pleaſed, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward content, and ſatisfaction, which she doth feele therin; ſo that she doth think, that there is nothing more to be deſyred in this life. But whereas the power of God, is infinit, and his workes, without limit, we muſt conceiue allwayes grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters, of his diuine Maieſty; and that as we diſpoſe our ſelues, (with the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34972:19"/>
grace of God) increaſing dayly in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and loue; he will impart his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and communicat his fauours more and more vnto vs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet true it is, that the leaſt of theſe diuine, and ſupernaturall communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is ſo ſublime, and tranſcending the capacity, of our weake vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and is ſo comfortable, and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the ſoul, not vſed to the like; that she doth eſteeme it very much, and thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that nothing more, or greater can be had, or deſyred in this life; But the, wayes, and inuentions of God, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municat himſelfe to ſoules, and bring them to his diuine loue, are many, and farre beyond our reach, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; and he is powerfull to giue them great gifts, and vnknowen fauours; though it is vnpoſſible for vs, to expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe by words, the fauours which we doe receiue in prayer, being ſupernaturall, vnleſſe his diuine Maieſty be pleaſed, to giue vs, the ability, to know the gift, and how to make it to be vnderſtood, by words; for there is great difference bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt feeling, and vnderſtanding, what we feele; and as our Holy Mother ſaith, it is one fauour to receiue a gift, and an other to cauſe vs to vnderſtand the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34972:20"/>
ſupernaturall, gift, which we receiue; <note place="margin">In her life chap. 17.</note> and an other, to know, how by words, or examples, to expreſſe it, and cauſe it, to be vnderſtood; by our directour;</p>
               <p n="3">3. And this, as a ſpeciall fauour was <note place="margin">In her life Chap. 30.</note> granted vnto her by God, aboue any, that I haue ſeene, or read that wrote of thoſe diuine communications; for the very cleereſt of them all, is obſcure enough; but she as one well experienced, and inſtructed by the holy Ghoſt, hath ſo plainly and clearly declared the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wayes, that in euery degree of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, God worketh in the ſoul, and what effects he doth produce in her, and what in theſe occaſions, the is to doe, and how to behaue her ſelfe, that the directour knoweth, reading her writings, what to examin, and the penitent how to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and declare herſelfe, that her dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour may be well informed of her ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and conceiue things aright; which otherwiſe, though neuer ſo learned, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout the experimentall knowledg of them, he could not vnderſtand, nor she expreſſe; and ſo the penitent ſoul by the Ghoſtly Father not vnderſtanding her, might ſuffer very much, and be hindred of her ſpirituall profit, as our Holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and others that she writ of, were;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34972:20"/>
and put rather backward, then forward in prayer, and vertue;</p>
               <p n="4">4. Now to ſpeake more of this degree, then is ſpoaken, in the firſt chapter, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſuperfluous; but deere Chriſtian ſoul, the more that ſuch matters, as theſe, are repeated, and ſome litle thing, giuen better to be vnderſtood, the more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, they are, and not in any way ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous; therefore out of her workes, I will adde (to what is formerly ſaid of theſe degrees, and of this in particular) that which I haue obſerued, which may be the better vnderſtood by this example.</p>
               <p n="5">5. A young chield, deſyring ſomwhat that he doth want, not able to help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, doth fall a crijng and is not at reſt, vntill his Mother, or nourſe doth take him, into her lappe or armes, and giueth him the breſt to ſuck; with this, he is ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and quiet, and when he hath taken ſufficiently, and his belly is full, as we may ſay, he begins to ſlumber and fall a ſleepe, and at laſt, he is ſoe heauily and deadly a ſleepe, that she takes the dugge out of his mouth, and placeth him where she pleaſe, to reſt, he not knowing, nor feeling what is done to him, or with him. In like manner, the ſoul in meditation is the child crijng for ſomwhat that she
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34972:21"/>
doth want, and is not at reſt, vntill his diuine Maieſty doth take compaſſion vppon her ſeing her weryed, and almoſt tired by the labour of the vnderſtanding and will, ſeeking to find him. then taking her into his lappe, he giueth her the teat of his holy preſence, which is ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, by which she begins to ſuck the ſweet milk of deuotion and diuine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and is thereby made ſilent, and contented, this is quiet prayer, then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken ſufficiently of that celeſtiall nectar, in that quiet content, with the dugge in her mouth (as we may ſay) or that diuine preſence, she is ſo ouer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted and ſatisfyed, and all the powers ſo ioyed, that by degrees they begin to ſlumber, or fall a ſleepe, forgetting by litle and litle, all things of the world; where they are, and what they doe; this is called, the ſleepe of the powers, yet is not the ſoul in a dead ſleepe, for she holdeth the dugge as yet in her mouth, and doe not omit to worke ſomewhat, at laſt she is ſo replenished with that diuine li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, as one drunke and quite ouercome, she falls into a dead ſleepe, she looſeth the dugge, and forgets abſolutly all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is in heauen or earth, and then she is put to reſt; yet; where or how, or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:34972:21"/>
by whom, she knoweth not, being drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and in gulfed in the diuine eſſence with all her powers vnited, the poore bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for that preſent, left quite forgotten, ſenſleſſe, and in a manner dead; and this is called vnion. that is, the ſoul and all the powers are vinted to the diuine eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and she becomes one with God, or as our Holy Mother ſayth, he taketh her and shut's her vpp within himſelfe. in the height of this vnion, the ſoul knoweth and vnderſtandeth nothing; but ſoone after, (for it holds not long) she knoweth what a great good she did enioy wherin all goodneſſe is. But now to the ſleepe of the powers I returne, which are not loſt, yet the ioy of the ſoul is ſo great, that she knoweth not what to doe with her ſelfe through the vehemency of loue, and she cannot containe her ſelfe, her ioy and glory is ſo great; she faine would cry out, to giue notice to all creatures, of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and paine, (for this exceſſe of loue is not without a delightfull paine; that all might partake thereof, and praiſe God; she doth feele thoſe effects in her ſelfe ſo perfectly, that they put her farre beyond her ſelfe;</p>
               <p n="6">6. And, then she doth ſpeake many words, of loue, in the praiſe of God, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34972:22"/>
any order, not knowing what to ſay, or doe. the will ſeemes to be in a kind of frensy with loue, the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding doth ſee ſo many things together, that she knoweth not what to fix vppon but is kept ſuſpended in admiration. the memory myndeth nothing, but what is preſent, ſo that the ſoul, in this ſpirituall frenſy and ſtrang diſpoſition, knoweth not what beſt to doe, whether to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, or ſpeake, to lough, or weepe; for she is in a reſtleſſe quietneſſe, and a ſweet reſt leſſneſſe through loue: then to thinke of returning, to vſe the things of this world againe, is very odious to her; to walke, is troubleſome; to ſpeake and not of him, is very painfull, to eate, is a kind of death, though nature doth require it, <note place="margin">Se her life chap. 37.</note> to ſleepe is worſe; in fine, all things which may in any wiſe hinder her, of the enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great a good, though for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and for her very health, doth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt her, and giueth her no ſatisfaction, nor content;</p>
               <p n="7">7. She doth not deſyre to ſee, or ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke with any, in this world, but with ſuch as are in the ſame frenſy, or ſick of the ſame diſeaſe, faine she would enioy God wholy, and know nothing but him; it ſeemes, that S. Augnſtine was ſick of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34972:22"/>
this diſeaſe, when he ſayd, our heart, o Lord, is allwayes vnquiet, vntill it reſt in thee;</p>
               <p n="8">8. Of the ſoul alſo in this ſpirituall drunkneſſe, it is ſaid in the canticles; he brought me into the winecellar, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 4.</note> in me charity, there she was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with the ſtrength of thoſe diuine liquours, she became wholy drunke with loue, she could goe no further, nor part the place, but fell into the armes, and ſweet embracements of her beloued, who placed his left hand vnder her head, and embraced her with his right; by the left, vnderſtand his mercy, keeping her from ſinne, leaſt she should fall, and by the right, his loue couering her ouer with many graces, bleſſings and fauours.</p>
               <p n="9">9. O Bleſſed drunknes, o happy fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishnes, o diuine frensy, o celeſtiall loue, who can tell your worth? O true louer of our ſoules Chriſt Ieſu, how forcibly with the odours of thy ſweet oyntments, do'ſt thou draw young Virgins, to witt, pious ſoules, after thee? if the loue of mortall creatures, be ſo forcible, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue people, of their witt, and the vſe of reaſon, and euen to cauſe them run naked and ſenſles about the ſtreetes, what shall we ſay then of this diuine lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue;</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:34972:23"/>
10. Theſe pious ſoules, O Lord, are in loue with thy infinit goodneſſe they are rauisht with thy rare beauty, they are ouer delighted with thy ſweetneſſe, they are not themſelues, they are vnquiet, and haue no reſt without thee; they feele in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly a burning fire, which doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them, and what is it? but that fire of charity, which thou ha'ſt ordered in them? they are by it ſtrongly in loue, yea drunke with loue, and quite beſyde themſelues; they doe loue, and know not what, but what they loue, is that which thou art; faine they would enioy thee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrely, and not by partes, being their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good; this they deſyre, this they inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re after, but know not, how it may be had; which maketh them wholy reſtleſſe, vntill they reſt in thee; for whether ſickly or healthy, ill, or well, liuing, or dead, in heauen, or hell; they regard not; ſo they may be with thee; for they are wholy thyne;</p>
               <p n="11">11. This diuine loue, doth leaue them no other force or ability, then to leaue themſelues wholy to God, and giue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that he may diſpoſe, all, and doe with them, what he pleaſe, and as he thinkes fitting; in ſo much, that then they cannot (though they would) apply them
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34972:23"/>
ſelues to any other thing, but to adheare to God alone; neither can they diuert themſelues neuer ſo litle, without great paine.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Heere they cannot but be attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, heare, ſee, and know his ſweet whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, pleaſant voyce, and Holy will, with great content; heere they may ſay with Samuell the Prophet, ſpeake o Lord for <note place="margin">1. <hi>king.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 10</note> thy ſeruant doth heare, that is to ſay, is attentiue to heare, and know, what thy will, and pleaſure is, to obey and fullfill it; and with Holy Dauid, ſay, I will hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ</hi> 84. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</note> that is, attend to what my Lord shall ſpeake in me; for he doth ſpeake peace vnto his people; as if he ſaid; I will giue care attentiuely to the words of my God, for they are of that Maieſty, and vertue, that though my ſoul were in darkneſſe, tempted, and troubled, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſound of his voyce diſperſeth all on a ſudden, leaueth a light, and inward pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to all my powers, and ſenſes, with ſo great ioy and ſatisfaction; that they are wholy recollected, and ſetled, and in a manner totally drowned in delight.</p>
               <p n="13">13. VVonderfull are the effects that God worketh in the ſoul, that is in this degree, farre ſurpaſſing thoſe of quiet prayer; for beſyde that she doth poſſeſſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34972:24"/>
his diuine Maieſty, more entirely, then in that; and that her ioy, and delight, are greater; her loue increaſeth to a great height, and her vertues are more ſolid, and her inward change is noted, by her outward behauiour, which she cannot couer, nor hyde; for all her actions are more ſtayd, and graue, then formerly; and she would not liue longer in this life, if she could; and her deſyre is ſo great to be with him in endleſſe reſt; that it were ſufficient to end her, if it were not that she doth think to doe him ſome ſeruice, in ſuffering the miſeryes, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of this world, for loue of him, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that as yet, she did very litle, or nothing, in his ſeruice, who, is goodneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe it ſelfe; and to whom she is ſo much obliged;</p>
               <p n="14">14. Her intention to pleaſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him, is pure without any ſelfe inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; she feare's no trubles, nor any thing of this world, but to diſpleaſe him, in the very leaſt imperfection, she doth proceede with all fidelity, and ſincerity; her conuerſation is only, and wholy in heauen, with, and for God; she doth not affect her owne content, or guſt, though neuer ſo ſpirituall, ſo much, as the honour of God, and to doe his will in all things;</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:34972:24"/>
15. O loue great is thy worth, and greater thy worke, they that doe poſſeſſe thee cannot but worke; they aſpire to great matters beyond theyr ability, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king all things poſſible to loue; therefore S. Paul ſayd, I can doe all things, in him, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Philip.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 13</note> who doth ſtrengthen me, Chriſt, they are neuer better feaſted, neuer more io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed, and delighted, neuer more ſweetly comforted, and contented, then when they ſuffer troubles, diſgraces, perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, torments, and euen death it ſelfe, for their beloued; therefore our Holy Mother S. Tereſa was wont to ſay to <note place="margin">In her life chap. 40.</note> God, (with whoſe loue she was inflamed) graunt me o Lord eyther to ſuffer, or to dye; for nothing but ſuffering for his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke could preſerue her lyfe; for in this she had ſome content: and her compagnion in her troubles, the venerable Father John a cruce, allwayes deſyred, either to ſuffer, or be contemned; and thus God is truly wonderfull in his ſaints; for what can be more admirable, then to ſee one deſyre and thirſt after thoſe things. which are contrary, yea, deſtructiue to nature, as to ſuffer torments, and death it ſelfe? but this is the priuiledg and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of diuine loue, which can haue no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt, but in the neſt, where it was bred.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34972:25"/>
and whence it came, ſo God loued the world, that he gaue them his only ſon, who ſuffered death with loue of them.</p>
               <p n="16">16. But you muſt obſerue, that though commonly, in this degree, the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and memory are ſo well employed, that they haue no ability or power to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelues to any other thing, then beholding and enioying what our Lord is pleaſed, to repreſent vnto them. Yet ſome tymes his Maieſty whoſe captiues they are, is pleaſed, to ſet them free, and at liberty; and though the will doth remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſtrongly vnited, they may employ themſelues in outward workes of vertue, as to frequent the quire, ſing, write, read, and other workes of charity, according to their ſtate of life, which in deede, is a great benefit; for then Martha, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the actiue, and contemplatiue life, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke two louing ſiſters, doe walke hand, in hand together; for the will (as Mary) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning in his ſweet repoſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull contemplation; they (as Martha) are well employed in outward actions, and ſome laudable occupations; yet they are not ſo attentiue outwardly, that they doe wholy forget the inward; and we may compare them to one, who hath one eye looking on what is outward, and the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34972:25"/>
other to what is inward; for they doe well know, that the will (which is their principall part) doth remaine there vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ioy; and that there, their moſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance ought to be; ſo that they are not perfectly in the one, nor in the other, but this good, that memory, and caſt of the eye, to what the will is a doing, bringeth to the ſoul, that when the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward employment is ended, they quickly deſyre, their former ſolitude, and are ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily retyred, and recollected, with the will; and then the ſoul doth remaine in great quietneſſe, tranquility, and inward peace, with admirable content and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, by reaſon all doe concurre and aſſiſt her, more ſeriouſly, compleatly, and perfectly to enioy her only good, and praiſe her God without impediment.</p>
               <p n="17">17. At other tymes. his diuine Maieſty is pleaſed to keepe the will and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding captiues, and vnited, leauing the memory, and imagination free at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and they finding themſelues alone and not regulated or directed by the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, are very vnquiet and troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſome; and doe endeauour to diſturbe the ſoul from her peaceable content and reſt, deſirous to bring the other powers, to themſelues, but though it be a cruell
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34972:26"/>
warre, they are able to effect nothing, wanting the aſſiſtance of the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and will; yet howſoeuer, they doe moleſt her much, and the imagination doth preſent ſo many things, runing from one, to an other, that the poore ſoul cannot doe what she would; by reaſon whereof, she doth often lament, and make her moane to his diuine Maieſty, that she is ſo diuided, and not wholy vnited in his loue, and praiſe; and at length, he cauſeth them for her comfort, to be vnited with the other powers, and to burne in, and with the ſame fire, in which the others are almoſt conſumed, looſing in a manner their naturall being, and liuing ſupernaturally in him. In this, and the like caſes, and occaſions, when any of the powers, are at liberty, and troubleſome, you muſt doe as is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſaid of quiet prayer, not regard them, nor attend to what they doe; but as a wiſeman taketh no notice of what a foole ſaith, or doth; ſo she muſt doe with them, and remaine, as much as she can poſſibly in her ſweet reſt, and repoſe. this is of importance to be knowen by ſuch as are come to theſe degrees of prayer.</p>
               <p n="18">18. And when a ſoul is come ſo farre
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34972:26"/>
as to begin to be wholy dead to all things of the world, and liue to God alone, her deſyre to be with him, and enioy him, is to vehement, and her paine thence ſo great, that if his diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty by a ſpeciall way, had not preuented it, and preſerued her, it were more then ſufficient (as is ſaid) to ſeperat the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, from the ſoul; for she can think vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon nothing, deſyre nothing, is ſatisfyed with nothing, but God alone, and the enioying of him, in his kingdome, of glory<hi>:</hi> which she cannot haue being a priſoner, in the miſerable and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble body; and therefore there is no death, ſo cruell, that could be offered, but she with vnſpeakable ioy, would endure; that ſet at liberty, she might the better, and without any impediment, poſſeſſe for euer, whom she doth, ſo deerely loue, our Holy Mother doth affirme that the paine and agony, that the ſoul hath in this degree, with that deſyre to be diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and liue with Chriſt, where he is ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne cleerly face to face, is ſuch, that the ſoul hath neede to haue great courrage to beare, and endure it. Therefore she aduiſeth that the ſoul in this occaſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> muſt reſolutly caſt her ſelfe wholy into Gods hands, and care; and leaue her ſelfe,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34972:27"/>
to his Holy diſpoſing in all things; for she doth know, that she cannot doe litle, or much in this caſe; neither hath she other ability, but to giue her conſent, and reſigne her will, to receiue thoſe, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, and embrace ſuch gifts, as his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſty is pleaſed to beſtow vppon her;</p>
               <p n="19">19. To this happineſſe ordinarily, they only come, who are mortified, voyde of ſelfe intereſt, diligent in Gods ſeruice, feruent in his loue, prompt to doe his will, carefull and ſincere, in all that is to his honour, glory, and praiſe; theſe are they, that his Maieſty bringeth into the wynecellar, to drinke of the choyſe and beſt, to eat at his owne table, to be in his priuat chamber, to reſt in the place of repoſe, and bed of delight; o how ſweet is their conuerſation, how diuine their embracement, how ſtrong their loue? he ſaid to his ſpouſe, with perpetuall charity I loued thee; Heere he giueth her a taſte, a begining, and a feeling of thoſe ioyes, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ieremy</hi> 31. <hi>v.</hi> 3.</note> and glory which are eternall; O who would not labour to attaine to ſo great happineſſe, which is ſo eaſily granted, and had.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Come deere Chriſtian ſoul, to him, by the practiſe of this Holy exerciſe of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34972:27"/>
prayer, put on once a good reſolution, and though perhaps in the begining you may haue ſome difficulty and be in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet in tyme with your perſeueran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, you shall be illuminated, and eaſed, come to him, I beſeech you, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo heauy loaden with ſinne, be not a shamed nor a frayd, for he is truly in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue with the leaſt and worſt of vs all, and I belieue farre more forward with loue of vs, then we can be with loue of him; this, his coming from heauen to earth, his Bitter Paſſion, his Pretious Blood shed, and his painfull death on the croſſe for vs; doth teſtify; come therefore with confidence to him, and you shall not be confounded, nor get a deniall, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſe; the manner how to come to him, King Dauid doth declare, ſaying; with all my heart I ſought after thee; (and not <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110 <hi>v.</hi> 145.</note> with a diuided heart) that is, that he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nothing elſe but God, for he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not to admit any other loue, into his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 145.</note> heart but his. and in an other verſe of the ſame pſalme, he ſaid, I cryed vnto thee o Lord with all my heart; and therefore he was heard; for his prayer, like incenſe, aſcended vnto God, from the altar of his penitent and louing heart, and it was ſo gratefull to his diuine Maieſty, that the <note place="margin">1. <hi>king<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:34972:28"/>
Scripture ſaith, that he was a man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to God's owne heart.</p>
               <p n="21">21. Be not thou then daunted, come to this thy louing Lord, take delight in prayer, in his holy conuerſation, and ſeruice; come with all thy heart, and then aske what thou wilt for thy good, and doubtleſſe it will be granted; the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thy heart he will regard; and if thou wilt diſpoſe thy ſelfe well, and be perſeuerant, thou mayſt obtaine this happy degree of prayer, and at laſt, his diuine Maieſty ſeing thee according to his owne heart, will crowne thy labours with many diuine fauours, and celeſtiall benedictions, euen in this life; and in the other, in the land of the liuing, with endleſſe glory, and felicity, and thou shalt ſee him face to face, where he is enioyed, and shall be praiſed by his Holy Saints and Angells, for all Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:34972:28"/>
               <head>THE IV. CHAPTER. Of the Prayer of vnion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IN the former chapters, you haue ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne how God doth bring a ſoul from the cares and troubles of the world, to a ſolitude formerly vnknowne, a ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſtate, where, in ſilence, he ſpeaketh to her heart; Now from that ſilent and quiet reſt, and from that delightfull ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe wherein the ſoul falleth a dijng to all things of this world, through loue; his diuine Maieſty taketh her wholy to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and doth conclude a ſpirituall mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage betwixt them both; in ſo much, that she is perfectly dead to all the world; that is to ſay, her affection is who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mortifyed, hauing no inclination to any thing created, and she is liuing only to, and in God, vnited to him, by a cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall coniunction; that is, by all her ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and powers, to hs diuine eſſence, and ſubſtance, in which, she is ſo farre carryed beyond her ſelfe not knowing how, or whither, that she cannot percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, whether she be in the body, or no, in the world, or out of it, for she is ſunke in the depth, and altogether in gulfed in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:34972:29"/>
that incomprehenſible ocean of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity, hauing loſt the vſe, of all her po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, and, inward, and outward ſenſes; and is become the ſame, and one ſpirit with him, and therefore it is called vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe two diſtinct things, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de one;</p>
               <p n="2">2. In this vnion she knoweth nothing, but that her ioy and ſatisfaction, is exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue great; but afterwards, she can well perceiue that her profit is farre tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that of the former degrees, and that her vertues are more ſolid, and of higher perfection; she in this vnion doth not labour more, but God doth worke in her, she is the patient, and he the, diuine agent, who doth produce thoſe wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effects, and make her admirable to the world, she hath enough to doe, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thoſe diuine fauours, and celeſtiall gifts, she is not ſatisfied with admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſeing the great goodneſſe, and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of God, towards ſuch as she is; which doth cauſe ſo great humility, and loue in her, that she would euen an nihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat her ſelfe in the preſence of ſo high a Maieſty; she is ſo drowned, that the body is quite forgotten and during that vnion, it is voyde of hearing, ſeing, and feeling, all her powers and ſenſes are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorpt,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34972:29"/>
and in gulfed ſo deeply in it, that there is no memory left of what they were meditating, thinking, reading, or doing, but their ioy cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt;</p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet, as it is formerly ſayd, this to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall vnion doth not continew long, befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſome of the powers are permitted to returne to their owne operations, the will ſtill remayning ſtrongly vnited, but they are ſo farre beſyde themſelues, that they can get no content or reſt; vntill they returne to their principall againe, and eat of the ſame meat, and drinke of the ſame liquour, and then they remaine ſuſpended, and vnited as formerly; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can they tell how long, or short a tyme, they are in that vnion; and though it were long, they are ſo ſwayed with ouer great delight, that it ſeemeth to them but very short;</p>
               <p n="4">4. I haue knowen one that was as yet but in the other degrees, and when the hour of prayer was ſpent, he could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be perſuaded, that it was ſo, for he thought really, that he had not beene more then the ſpace of one Aue Maria in it; not knowing what prayer he was in; what shall we thinke then of this? cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the leaſt part of it, cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34972:30"/>
by all the eloquence, and rethorick of the world, as it is; much leſſe, the reſt, which is more;</p>
               <p n="5">5. O how admirable and farre ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all vnderſtanding it is, to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how Gods Holy diuinity doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in, and penetrat the whole ſubſtance and eſſence of the ſoul, leauing in her, a perfect impreſſion of himſelfe, that she is no more what she was, but truly deified, altogether in gulfed in the bleſſed diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, now quite forgetfull of her ſelfe, and all that is in heauen and earth; for she is in poſſeſſion, of him, who contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all, and is more then all, and is her all; ſo that in the other, she may be well ſayd, to be a dijng, but in this, to be truly dead, as you ſee, but to God alone, in whom she doth liue, and who doth liue in her.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This is a moſt happy ſtate, a bleſſed reſt, a ſweet repoſe, a heauenly drunknes, a ioyfull alteration, a louing embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a delightfull vnion, a diuine trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, a totall Deification, and a blisfull marriage, confirmed; and ſigned with no leſſe then his owne moſt Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diuinity, that as a bride and bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome, they are one ſpirit, she is parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of his glory, looketh to his family,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:34972:30"/>
and attendeth only to thoſe things, which belong to him, and to his honour, glory, and praiſe; and he hath care of her, and of what doth belong to her; now she is ſo burning with his loue and ſo ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous of his affaires, that she is neuer idle, she doth thirſt vehemently after the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of ſinners, and ſaluation of ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, as a thing belonging to her beloued, and to his honour, and glory; and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe, and effect this great and difficult worke, she doth find her ſelfe ſtout and courragious, and would giue a thouſand liues moſt willingly (if she could) to gaine one ſoul, and therefore her prayers to God, are many, and haue no end; her teares and pennances for them, are great. no troubles can breake her, no perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, feare her, detractions doe not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue her, murmuration and diffamation doe not diſquiet her, she taketh contentedly, and ioyfully, all diſgraces, ſo she may gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne but one ſoul to God, and in this, she is continually labouring; and to make his goodneſſe knowen to all, that they may loue, and ſerue him, and with greater fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour allwayes praiſe him; and that they may dayly increaſe in all vertue, and perfection.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To heare any to flatter, or praiſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:34972:31"/>
her, is a torment to her, to ſee her ſelfe eſteemed, and honoured, is her greateſt affliction, for she cleerly knoweth, that she deſerues it not, and what good, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, or gift is ſeene in her, is not from her ſelfe, but from the fountaine of all grace, mercy, and goodneſſe, her heauenly ſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, without any merit on her part; and therefore to him she doth referre all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and praiſe, to whom alone it is due;</p>
               <p n="8">8. The reſolutions of ſuch as come to this ſtate, to doe ſome heroyick workes, for the loue, honour and glory of God, are as ſtrange, and admirable as the reſt; they know not what to doe with themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, they are ſo tranſported by loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond themſelues; and this loue doth ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them and ſtrengthen them to doe, what to others might ſeeme vnpoſſible, hence our Holy Mother S. Tereſia did <note place="margin">In her life chap. 18.</note> make that admirable vowe, to doe in all things, what she conceiued, or should be informed, were moſt to God's honour, and glory, or of moſt perfection: which is a wonderfull thing; and a rare act. to tye her ſelfe ſo ſtrictly vnder the penalty of a mortall ſin, doing the contrary. But this is the efficacy and effect of diuine lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, and this she did exactly performe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:34972:31"/>
her life. and her deſyre of god's glory and honour was ſo great that she prayed earneſtly that his diuine Maieſty would depriue her of the fauours which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed vppon her, and giue them to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that might doe more good with them, for the conuerſion of ſoul's, and the good of his Church, only that he might be the more honored, glorified and praiſed;</p>
               <p n="9">9. One of theſe ſoules, though but ſimple and ignorant; will doe more good in the Church of God, then many elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent preachers with all their art and learning. Conſider S. Francis, who had no learning, and our Holy Mother, a ſimple woman, yet it is admirable to ſee what great good they haue done in the Church of God; and how many thouſand ſoules by their meanes were, and are dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaued; and ſo of others, who did the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke; the ſpirit of God doth efficaciouſly concurre with them, and their words, doe powerfully moue ſuch as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with, to a vertuous life, and the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of God. of theſe things you may read more at large in her life, and workes; for I doe ſpeake but briefly of them heere, to giue ſome ſmall notice of what his diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Maieſty is graciouſly pleaſed to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:34972:32"/>
in the ſoules which diſpoſe themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and endeauour in what they can, to loue, and ſerue him; that others may be encourraged to vſe this Holy exerciſe of prayer, in which God doth communicat his fauours, and gifts to deuout ſoules, and giue them a taſte of thoſe ioyes, which are in heauen. I beſeech his diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne maieſty to graunt this gift of prayer to many, for his glory, and the good of his Holy Church. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>THE V. CHAPTER. Of ſeuerall other eleuations of the ſpirit, and how they differ from vnion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. OVr Holy Mother doth declare, that they that come to perfect vnion, commonly haue viſions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations, extaſis, flights and rapts, and that though, the extaſis, flights, and rapts ſeeme to be one, and the ſame thing, yet in truth, they are not, as they who haue experience of them, by their effects can eaſily obſerue in themſelues, I shall touch briefly ſome of them heere, and ſo with God's help, end this worke; leauing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:34972:32"/>
the reader to peruſe them more fully, in her workes, whence I haue collected the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and where they are farre more plainly expreſt, then I doe heere.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The difference betwixt vnion, and theſe others, and of theſe betwixt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, is knowen by their effects. and firſt the effects of vnion, are inward only, the ſoul alone enioying that happineſſe, of which I ſpoake in the former chapter, for the body is ſenſleſſe, and deſtitute of any operation, or comfort; I ſpeake of the totall, or perfect vnion; but in the exta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, or ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the effects are inward, and outward; for the body is not deſtitute of its operations; alſo one may reſiſt the vnion; though with great paine, but not the others; for often on a ſudden, the ſoul is ſurpriſed, and carryed away, she then not thinking of God, and vnleſſe the rapt be very great, or in the height (for then she knowes nothing as in the vnion) the ſenſes are not loſt, and one may perceiue, that the head is drawen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter she ſpirit, and ſomtymes by the force of the ſpirit, the whole body, is eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vpp into the ayer, and the party then ſeing the body, ſo farre aboue ground, doth begin to feare, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at it; yet in this, both body, and ſoul
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:34972:33"/>
haue great comfort, and ioy.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Heere the ſoul doth obſerue the great power of God, to whom there can be no reſiſtance; but when he is pleaſed, he will eleuat both ſoul and body, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout our conſent, and againſt our will; for at theſe tymes, as we are nothing, ſo we can doe nothing with our ſelues, but he, as Lord of all, diſpoſeth of his owne, as he thinks fit, ſo that the ſoul is carryed in theſe rapts, she knoweth not whither, how, or by whom, but away she muſt goe; and for her greater comfort, his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſty is often pleaſd to shew vnto her, the kingdome of heauen, and what glory, he hath prepared there for his true ſeruants, for euer; at other ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, the Angells; then ſome ſaints, alſo his magnificent power, and he doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2. Gor.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 4</note> her vnderſtand high miſteryes, and great ſecrets, of which, as S. Paul ſaith, it is not lawfull to ſpeake; alſo she doth ſee the Queene of Angells, the Mother, of God, in great glory, and the ſacred humanity, of our Sauiour, in vnſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Maieſty, and glory; and when he is ſo pleaſed she doth enioy the ſight, and company of the moſt Holy Trinity; and at other tymes she is endued with the ſpirit of Prophecy; and knowledg of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:34972:33"/>
things to come: and the vnderſtanding of the Holy Scripture. our Holy Mother <note place="margin">In her life chap. 37. &amp; Manſ. 7. chap. 1.</note> doth relate (as by obedience she was commanded) how the holy Trinity did appeere vnto her in the very center of her ſoul, and that she could not but ſee euery perſon, and the admirable glory, and Maieſty, that was preſent; she did ſpeake to euery perſon, in particular, and they to her, in which, her ioy, and content, was ſo great, that it cannot be imagined; and it is no wonder, if the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes should not returne to their owne functions from ſo great happineſſe, that they doe there enioy; neither would they willingly, vnleſſe it were as ſeruants doe, to obey and fullfill the will and command of their Lord; for his Maieſty will often haue it ſo; either for her ſpirituall profit, the good of others, or his owne honour and glory.</p>
               <p n="4">4. She alſo doth relate how she was in a rapt eleuated and taken to behold the kingdome and Glorious inhabitants of heauen, her owne parents, and ſome frends, and was brought to the bleſſed throne of God, to behold how the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <note place="margin">Se her life chap. 38.</note> word, the ſecond perſon of the holy Trinity, the ſonne of God, is reſident in the boſome of his Father, and she ſaith,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:34972:34"/>
that the ſoul in theſe occaſions can doe nothing of it ſelfe, nor behold litle or much, but only, what our Lord will haue her to ſee, or know; and as there be ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall degrees of eleuations, of the ſpirit, or rapts; in euery one of them, the light is greater, the knowledg more and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, the alienation from all things crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, more perfect, the vertues more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, humility chiefly, more profound; and the loue of God, increaſing, (as they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend, one degree, after an other,) is ſo ordent and vehement, that the ſoul doth loath to liue on earth, and her abſence, or ſeparation from God, is ſo heauy a loade, that she doth liue but a painfull life, or rather, a tormenting Martyrdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and lingering death; ſo that all her deſyre, is to be diſſolued, and be with Chriſt; yet though the paine, which she doth ſuffer, is very great, her inward ioy, is no leſſe, if not more; but you shall ſee what she ſpeakes of rheſe degrees.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The firſt after vnion, is, when the ſoul (like vnto a flame proceeding, or aſcending from a well kindled fire) bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the fire of diuine loue, goeth out of her ſelfe, aſcending vpwards, and ſome tymes it goeth to a great height farre beyond the fire, whence, it doth
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:34972:34"/>
proceede, and this doth ſeeme to thoſe, that went no further, to be the ſame with vnion, but it differs much. For vnion, is like to the fire, which only burneth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, not giuing any flames aſcending vpwards; but this going out of her ſelfe, is like flames aſcending vpwards from the fire, and not to the fire it ſelfe; ſo that this fire increaſing, and not able (by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of its vehemency) to containe it ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe from blaſing foorth, the ſweet wynd of the Holy Ghoſt blowing on it, the ſoul is eleuated out of her ſelfe, and as this firye flame increaſeth, it doth more and more conſume in her, all terrene af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and leaueth her, farre purer, and with greater freedome, and liberty, then in vnion; and though she knoweth not how it came to paſſe, yet she cannot but admire to ſee ſuch an alteration and change in her ſelfe; and her profit to be farre greater, and with very great ioy.</p>
               <p n="6">6. At other tymes, his diuine Maieſty is pleaſed that the ſoul be ſtruck and woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the very heart with a fearefull noyſe in the moſt inward of her ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, by a certaine delicat, ſubtile, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netratiue impulſe, and, as it were with a firy dart<hi>:</hi> or bolt on a ſudden, proceeding
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:34972:35"/>
from a thunder she not knowing how or by whom it came and though she hath hence great paine, her ioy and comfort, is farre greater then in the former, and though this noyſe is not heard, with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall eares, for it is inward, and a very ſilent noyſe, yet inſtantly heard, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood by the ſoul; and she doth cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and perfectly know that she is ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vppon, by God as with a whiſtle and that she cannot but heare it, and ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feele a great certainty of his preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and it is of that Maieſty and efficacy, that it cauſeth all the powers and ſenſes inſtantly to be recollected, attentiue, and giue their attendance, though at that preſent, they were much diſtracted, and they dare not then moue, or ſtire; and this celeſtiall call, impulſe, or firy dart, doth ſo inflame her, that she is burning and a conſuming with the fire of diuine loue, penetrating through her very bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wells and the very inward ſubſtance of the ſoul; and her paine by reaſon of the wound, and the vehemency of loue, is ſo great, that she cannot containe her ſelfe, but lament, and with moſt ſweet, and amorous words, complaine of her paine, (not being able to doe otherwiſe) to her deerely beloued, whom she knoweth to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:34972:35"/>
be preſent, and will not manifeſt himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, which is a ſpurre to forward and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment both loue and paine; and though this paine is with vnſpeakable delight, it doth not continue long, but cometh and goeth, and allwayes doth leaue the ſoul inflamed with diuine loue; her deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to pleaſe him, and ſerue his maieſty in great matters, doth increaſe; and her on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare, is, leaſt she should become vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratfull, for this, and his other great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, and benefits, which doth encour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage her dayly to better her life, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent him the more.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Note that in this rapt the powers and ſenſes are not ſuſpended nor drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but all ſtand in admiration, to ſee the ſoul in ſo great paine, worthy of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and yet with vnſpeakable delight; they wonder much what this should be, and they can neither helpe, nor diſturbe her, but remaine in their attendance, with admiration. In theſe degrees, it doth happen that the ſoul hath many ſtrong and ſudden motions, when one doth heare a good ſermon, or God well ſpoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, or praiſed, or muſick, or at the ſight of ſome ſweet, and deuout picture; and this cometh with an impulſe in the depth or moſt inward of the ſoul ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:34972:36"/>
ſudden, and ſwift, that she can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſiſt it, more then a chyld, to a Gyant, but away she is taken, and eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſometymes aboue all that is created, where she hath the viſions, and reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions formerly mentioned, and with the greatneſſe of the glory and Maieſty which she beholdeth in God, she is much terrified, and doth conceiue a reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall feare, which cauſeth the very haires of her head to ſtand, and then she doth grieue, that she, or any other euer offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded à Lord of ſo high, and incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible a dignity, power, and Maieſty; and ſome tymes it is ſo exceſſiue, that the body in the rapt is eleuated forcibly a great height from the earth, as loathing all things on earth, and tending to the place, where it doth expect to be in end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe happineſſe;</p>
               <p n="8">8. Neither is the ſoul, and powers for a long tyme after theſe great rapts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly themſelues; for they are not yet out of that ſweet ſleepe, or riſen from that delightfull drunkneſſe, for they had <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 35. <hi>v.</hi> 9.</note> taken plentifully of the varietyes, and abundance of his houſe, and drunke without meaſure of the torrent of thoſe diuine liquours, with ſo exceſſiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light that they for a tyme after know
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:34972:36"/>
not where they are, or what they doe.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Alſo when they returne to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues all things of this world are ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtfull, and diſpleaſing to them, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great ioy they had, that they haue an auerſion from them, and would not daine, if they could, to vſe the leaſt of them;</p>
               <p n="10">10. She declareth an other degree, or ſort of rapt, which she doth call, a flight of the ſoul, farre different from the reſt and greater, this she doth compare to a fire that ſuddenly falling, doth fire, and burne all, whence proceedeth a great flame; ſo as the ſoul is ſuddenly fired all ouer, and doth burne ſo ſtrongly with the fire of diuine loue, that her ſpirit li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vnto a great flame with a moſt ſwift flight getteth out of herſelfe, in ſuch a delicat and ſubtile manner, that it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, and in an inſtant she is placed where she doth ſee and vnderſtand ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great miſteryes together, with all clearneſſe, and truth; and she doth not only ſee the Holy Trinity and ſpeake with euery perſon, but alſo doth obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſome particular fauour of each of them.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Likewiſe she doth relate that God doth shew how all creatures are contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:34972:37"/>
in his diuine eſſence, and may be ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne as in a faire chriſtiall glaſſe; ſuppoſe, ſaith she, that there were a great round criſtiall glaſſe, greater then all the world, without which there is nothing, and in which all things are included, and ſeene very cleerly; the ſame conceiue of God, in whom really, and truly, all things are contayned, and euen the very thoughts, words, and deedes, of euery one in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, may be plainly ſeene; she ſayth that this viſion was one of the greateſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, which God did, vnto her, and that a ſoul hath great neede of a ſtrong courage, to behold what are there, chiefly the horrid and foul ſinns committed againſt his diuine Maieſty, and the many abuſes and iniuryes which dayly are do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne to him in the world; this is able and ſufficient (she ſayes) to cauſe a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and an abſolute diuiſion of the ſoul from the body, if God had not giuen her ſtrength to bere it, or diſpoſed of her otherwiſe;</p>
               <p n="12">12. She doth alſo ſpeake of an other ſort of rapt farre beyond the reſt, and ſaith, that it is more then a rapt, for it is a very vehement and eminent rapt, and of great value and worth, this ſuddenly, at the hearing. God well ſpoaken of, or
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:34972:37"/>
calling to mynd that he is abſent, whom she doth loue moſt entirely, and often without any of both, she doth find in her ſelfe a vehement motion, and deſyre to be with him, which is ſo forcible, that in an inſtant it doth penetrat the ſoul wholy; she knoweth not how it is, but doth feele it, and is not able to reſiſt it, and she is taken, and powerfully carryed beyond all that is created, and placed in a ſtrang ſolitude, deſolat, and deſtitute of any comfort from heauen and earth, and she doth conceiue, that none of any of both, would keepe her company, or be a comfort to her, in that deſolation; neither doth she deſyre any comfort or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny from them, but would there willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer and dye.</p>
               <p n="13">13. And it doth happen as she ſaith, that his diuine Maieſty doth communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat him ſelfe to her in ſo ſubtile and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable a way, that it cannot be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, leſſe expreſſed by any, but by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; but she hath ſo cleere a knowledge then left in her, of his greatneſſe and goodneſſe, and his other incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perfections, that it doth increaſe her loue, and augment her paine and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; loue doth burne, and conſume her, her deſyre to be with him, is able to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:34972:38"/>
ſeparat the ſoul from the body, and she doth not know how to help her ſelfe, but by death, and therefore dye she would, to enioy his bleſſed preſence in glory; this torment is the greater, that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of him, is ſo perfect and cleere; notwithſtanding he doth abſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, which addeth much to her affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p n="14">14. In other degrees, or rapts, the ioy doth mitigat her paine, but in, this, she is deſtitute of all ioy, or conſolation; and left in the furnace of tribulation, which is a very ſtrong martyrdome, and ſo painfull, that as ioy, and ouer much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, in the other degrees, did ſuſpend the powers, and ſenſes; ſo paine doth in this. and it is of ſo great vehemency, that the very body doth partake with her, of it, and it is ſo diſioynted, that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the members ſeeme broaken, and for many dayes after no one member can be moued without great, and vnexplicable paine.</p>
               <p n="15">15. It is able to moue a ſtony heart, to read how our Holy Mother doth deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be it, in her life, and what lamentation <note place="margin">In her life chap. 20.</note> and loud cryes she giueth out, to expreſſ her paine, only deſyrous to be diſſolue and be with Chriſt, and for her greate
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:34972:38"/>
torment, in that ſolitude, she is put in mynd of that verſe; I watch, and am as she <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 101 <hi>v</hi> 3.</note> ſolitary ſparrow alone, in the toppe, or roofe of the houſe; and she thinketh then that she is ſo; and in that caſe, and ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe; she doth remember theſe words, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ</hi> 41. <hi>v.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.</note> (without procuring it) where is thy God. as if it were ſaid, to her, where is he, in whom thou ha'ſt placed all thy confidence, where is he? why doth not he now helpe thee in this diſtreſſed caſe? hath he ſo forſaken thee, whom thou do'ſt, ſo deerely loue, and ſeeke af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? now he hath left thee deſtitute of all comfort, and conſolation; if he had lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thee, he would not forſake thee thus? are all thy labours come to this, that thou art left in deſolation, without comfort, or helpe from heauen and earth? where is thy God? this (God ſo permitting) doth duble her paine, and increaſe her deſyre, ſo vehemently to ſee, and be with him, that it is ſufficient to take away ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny liues, if she had them; and that ſaying of S. Paul was repreſented vnto her, I <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>v.</hi> 14.</note> am crucified to the world, and the world to me, ſo that she remaines in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt torment that may be imagined, as it were crucifyed, betwixt heauen and earth;</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:34972:39"/>
16. Our Holy Mother doth compare this paine to the paines of Purgatory, it is ſo exceſſiue, and when the ſoul doth perceiue that his diuine Maieſty, is to bring her into this ſolitude, and angui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shes of death (for truly it is no other) she naturally doth feare, and tremble; but once that she is in it, she would not be out of it: true it is, that the ſenſitiue or inferiour part cannot but loath it, being ſo ouer painfull, and apt to ſeparat the body from the ſoul; yet the ſuperiour, or ſpirituall part, taketh content in ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, for the loue of God; eſteeming it, as in deede it is, of great value, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. fot in this, she is moſt like vnto our Sauiour Crucified, deſtitute of any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 27. <hi>v.</hi> 46.</note> from heauen or earth, which cauſed him to ſay, my God, my God, as what ha'ſt thou for ſaken me; and therefore she doth reiect all that formerly were wont to comfort her, to remaine in this paine, and conformity to Chriſt our Sauiour ſuffering, for as the gold by fire, she in this, is tryed, purified, and refined, as if she were come from Purgatory; her loue is now purer, and ſo exceſſiue great, that nothing can content or ſatisfy her bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deſyre, but the poſſeſſion, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of God wholy as he is, and not
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:34972:39"/>
any particular part of him; and ſince she cannot iuſtly procure her owne death, to be with him; with great tenderneſſe, of heart, she doth lament, and bewayle her long bannishment, reſigning her ſelfe wholy to his diuine diſpoſing, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly praying that her liuing as yet, in this caſe, may be very highly, to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory, which she doth allwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes, and in all things regard more, then her ſelfe; and deſyre, rather then her eaſe, or to be free from her paine, though she were certaine, it should continue to the world's end.</p>
               <p n="17">17. In this paine, dying life, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of loue, towards God, our Holy Mothers ſoul was commonly in her later dayes, and the impulſes of loue, were ſo penetratiue, and forcible, in her; that with the vehemency of one great impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of loue, her pure and bleſſed ſoul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the body, (not of any other ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) and aſcended into glory, where she doth moſt happily enioy him, whom she ſo deerely loued; this she did declare appeering to the venerable Mother Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therin of Ieſus Prioreſſe of Beas the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day of her death; I beſeech his diuine Maieſty, to grant this diuine loue, to all that are deſyrous to ſerue, and loue
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:34972:40"/>
him, with truth, though it be with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great paine, yea, coſt what it may. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>THE VI. CHAPTER. Of the manner of inward ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, viſions, and reuelations, and how to diſcerne the true from the falſe.</head>
               <p n="1">1. SOme ſpeaches, and viſions are outward, as when a thing is heard, or ſeene, with corporall eares, and eyes; ſo one man doth ſee an other preſent, and heare him diſcourſing, or ſpeaking of ſomwhat; Others are inward, that is, heard, ſeene, or vnderſtood farre within the ſoul. of theſe ſome are imaginary, others intellectuall; the imaginary, is, when a thing is repreſented in ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, or shape, to the eyes of the ſoul; as for example, when you frame in your mynd, the image of your frend, who is abſent; you doe ſee him inwardly, in a manner, as if he were perſonally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, you ſee his geſtures, and behauiour, and may be moued, out of that ſight, to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:34972:40"/>
loue him, or grieue for his abſence, or to hate him, and his ill condition, or beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and thus Chriſt our Sauiour or his ſaints may appeere, in the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and it is called therefore ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But the intellectuall, is without any image, shape, or forme; yet of more certainty, then the others, for ſpirits ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no shape nor forme, but being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, they ſee, and vnderſtand, in a more perfect manner, then in the other wayes; what each other doth intend. as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells doe ſee, and cleerely vnderſtand, one, an other in heauen: and in theſe three wayes, there are ſpeaches, viſions, and reuelations; the firſt is moſt ſubiect to deceipt, the ſecond not ſo much, by farre; for the deuil can turne him ſelfe into the shape, of an Angell of light, to deceiue; but the laſt, is leaſt of all ſubiect to deceit, as ſurpaſſing the actiuity, or reach of the deuil; and therefore is moſt ſecure, and without danger.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But that his wyles, and wayes may be knowen, and diſcouered; and that a ſoul may not be much troubled, to know (if she hath any viſions or reuelations) whether they be true, or falſe. our Holy Mother doth lay downe certaine ſignes,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:34972:41"/>
and tokens, to diſcerne the true, from the falſe, as when they are from God or the deuil, and alſo to know when they may be framed by the imagination, which in ſome is very liuly, and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Firſt obſerue, that when any words, are ſpoaken outwardly, or inwardly, if they be from God, they come with cleerneſſe; that of the deuil doth bring darkneſſe. alſo when they are from the deuil you may reſiſt, and reiect them, and diuert your vnderſtanding, and not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vnto them, when you pleaſe; but if they be from God, doe what you may, and diuert your ſelfe, neuer ſo much, you cannot hinder it, but muſt euen againſt your will, heare, and ſee, what is ſaid, or done, ſo cleerly and diſtinctly, that you shall not forget, one ſillable, though you would, all doe remaine ſo perfectly prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the vnderſtanding. alſo by this, his diuine Maieſty, will haue vs to know, that he is all omnipotent and the true Lord of all, who alone, hath all do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer vs, and whoſe power, and will, none can reſiſt, but muſt ſee, heare and vnderſtand, when, and what he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; and if the words be of Prophecy, they shall hardly be euer forgotten till
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:34972:41"/>
they take effect, for they leaue ſo great a certainty of their truth, in the ſoul; that she cannot but belieue, that all will be truly performed accordingly, as they are foretold, though by all reaſon, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, and the preſent difficultyes, they ſeeme vnpoſſible. of this she had great experience;</p>
               <p n="5">5. Note alſo, that ſome vnderſtandings, are ſo pregnant, and the imagination ſo liuly, that they frame and repreſent things very perfectly, and perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues that they ſee, and heare, what truly they doe not; but it is a thing inuented, according to their fancy, by themſelues. and it may be vnderſtood thus; when a thing is framed by themſelues, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerue, and perceiue the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding working, and framing what it would, and producing the words though neuer ſo ſubtily; alſo they are dumbe words, without any light, or good effect in the ſoul, alſo you may omit to ſee, heare, or ſpeake, when you pleaſe; but when they are from God, they come with light, and cleerneſſe, as is ſaid, and you cannot diuert your ſelfe, but muſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and the vnderſtanding is ſet at reſt, and in ſo great quietneſſe that of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, you muſt giue eare to what is ſaid, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:34972:42"/>
ſee what is preſented, and they are not dumbe words, but his words, are words, and workes together; and ſome tymes, though they be not words of deuotion, but of inſtruction, admonition, or repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, in an inſtant, they doe diſpoſe, and recollect the ſoul, and doe moue her to a louing tenderneſſe, and illuminat, quiet, and delight her; which, words, or ſights framed by the deuil, or our ſelues, cannot doe; and when the ſoul is in any affliction, temptation or aridity, though neuer ſo great, at the hearing of one word, or at any ſight, that is from God, all doth vanish away ſuddenly; she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining with great light, quietneſſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and ioy. which the others doe not; by this, the ſoul that is practiſed, doth well know, when they are from God, or no; and how powerfull, and operatiue his word is; and of what grear efficacy, his viſions are;</p>
               <p n="6">6. Moreouer, you may obſerue, that in an inſtant (which is to be well noted) many long ſentences, and arguments are ſpoaken, and vnderſtood (when it is from God) and the ſoul, shall remember euery word, and ſillable, which in a long tyme, and with much ſtudy, and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, the vnderſtanding would not be
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:34972:42"/>
able to frame, or compaſſe. Alſo they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with ſuch Maieſty, and efficacy, that when they are reprehenſiue, they cauſe the ſoul to tremble and shake, and if they be of loue, they make her to, long, languish, and in a manner, melt to nothing with loue, but when they are falſe, they worke no ſuch effect; and therefore the ſoul doth make litle account of them, and doe caſt them at naught; ſo that neither the deuil, nor our imagination, though neuer ſo quick, and liuly, can worke, or cauſe thoſe good effects in the ſoul.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In like manner, when the words, ſpeeches, or viſions are from the deuil, they doe leaue, and worke euil effects, and not good, in the ſoul; as darkneſſe, aridity, diſquietneſſe; and though the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil doth worke ſome ſenſible guſt, in that occaſion, which may deceiue begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and thoſe of no experience; yet they who once taſted of the true viſions, and ſpeeches, will inſtantly know the difference betwixt them; for they that are from God, doe leaue in the ſoul a guſt, very ſweet, pleaſing, forcible, and dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable, with great quietneſſe, and it is ſo deeply imprinted, that it cannot be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gott. but that other which is falſe, doth ſuddenly decay and vanish away, as if
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:34972:43"/>
there neuer were any ſuch thing; neither is the ſoul any thing betterred by them.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Alſo the deuil is neuer able to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fit, or appeere with that maieſty, light, cleerneſſe, and liulyneſſe, with which our Sauiour doth appeere; for he doth come ſo reſplendent and glorious, and his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is ſo beautifull, that the ſoul cannot but know that it is he, and often his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and her ioy, at his preſence, are ſo great, that she is wholy rauished and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of all forces; and this doth leaue in her, a true feeling knowledg, that he alone, is abſolute Lord, of heauen and earth; and with this, she is extreamly comforted, hauing a liuly impreſſion of him printed in her vnderſtanding, euen after he is parted, which the deuil cannot effect, let him doe what he can. In this manner his diuine Maieſty was preſent for ſome yeares with our Holy Mother whereſoeuer she went; But in the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall viſion, which is more euident, eminent, and more ſecure, from all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, (being very ſupernaturall, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the Angelicall manner of knowing, or vnderſtanding) without words, formes, or shapes, or any image, by a notion ſo diuine, with admirable
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:34972:43"/>
light, and cleerneſſe, she doth know, and ſee, in the very center of the ſoul, the moſt Bleſſed Trinity; and in this manner, the three perſons, remayned in our Holy Mother, as wittneſſes of what she did, and they did often admonish, and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warne her, to preuent ſome imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, into which in occaſions, she had fallen, if she were not foretold of them; and she was ſo replenished with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of diuine Miſteryes, and thoſe chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fely, of our Holy faith, that she was able to diſpute, and conuince the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned proteſtants, shew their errours, and make the truth plainly, and euidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere. this she doth write, at which, I thinke, none can admire, she being full of diuine wiſdome, taught and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the truth it ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="9">9. And obſerue that theſe high and great viſions, are not as a certaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, or ſome influence of the diuinity, which in quiet prayer, vnion, or other degrees of ſupernaturall prayer, are had; but in theſe, is the bleſſed body, and proper perſon of Chriſt himſelfe, true God and man, the very ſon of the Glorious, and immaculat Virgin Mary, of which, the ſoul cannot doubt; neither can the deuil, as is ſaid repreſent ſuch
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:34972:44"/>
great beauty, glory, and Maieſty, with which our Sauiour doth appeere, for all the glory that can be imagined, is but a darke cloud compared with this. and heere alſo is the moſt Holy Trinity it ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, the very diuine eſſence, one God, and three perſons, and each of them doe ſpeake to her, and she to them, and of euery of them, she doth begg, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſome ſpeciall fauour or gift.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And note, that ſome tymes, there are wordes, without any viſion, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not knowing how, or whence they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, but they are heard, with the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eares; other tymes inwardly, in the very depth of the ſoul, but cleerly, and perfectly vnderſtood; alſo there are vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and no words, yet the ſoul doth get great benefit thereby; and there are viſions and words to gether. But in what kind ſo euer they be, the ſoul, by the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and effects mentioned, will eaſily know, whether they be good, or no, true, or falſe, which is a very great comfort to her; moreouer when the viſions, and ſpeeches, are true, they worke ſo effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually in the ſoul, that she doth find her inclination to vices, and imperfections, decay, and true vertue taking roote in her, which the deuil with all his witt, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:34972:44"/>
wyles, is not able to doe. Bleſſed be God who hath prouided ſo well for his owne ſeruants<hi>:</hi> he is truly wonderfull in all his workes, and as he is omnipotent, ſo nothing is to his diuine Maieſty vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
               <p n="11">11. But though theſe ſignes, heere layd downe, (by which one may diſcerne the true from the falſe, and the good from the bad) are very good; yet she doth aduiſe, <note place="margin">In her life chap. 19.</note> though the fauours be great that none muſt truſt litle, or much, to himſelfe, or his owne iudgment, but in all, and euery thing, be circumſpect and prudent, only acquainting his Ghoſtly Father, or dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, with what viſions, or other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, God doth grant vnto him, and both of them, muſt not diuulge any of them, but vſe all ſecrecy, and ſilence, commending it to God, vntill tyme doth try the truth; or his diuine Maieſty, by ſome other way, doth make it manifeſt, and knowen, if he will haue it ſo. for the deuil is apt, to tempt, and deceiue, and our nature is prone, and inclined to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per eſteeme, and vaine glory, on ſmall occaſions, much more in theſe like;</p>
               <p n="12">12. And ſuch as are deſirous of true perfection, muſt be carefull not to affect, or ſeeke after ſupernaturall guſts, viſions
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:34972:45"/>
and reuelations; for it is a true token of an vnmortifyed ſpirit, litle humility, and much preſumption; and to theſe God doth not commonly giue thoſe fauours; but to the humble, that thinke themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues altogether vnworthy of any ſuch; for humility in this way of Spirit, doth preuaile much with God, and gayneth all.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Moreouer if in theſe ſupernaturall degrees, you find your prayer allwayes; after one manner; and your guſtes, and quietneſſe of ſpirit, at all tymes to be the ſame; your prayer is to be ſuſpected, not to be right, but from Sathan; and in viſions, if you can for a long tyme wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout alteration, behold that which doth appeere, whether it be our Sauiour, or any Saint, it is to be eſteemed, an illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and deceit of the deuil; for all theſe great vnions, rapts and viſions are of no continuance, but ſpeedily doe alter, and paſſe away; that is to ſay, they doe not continew in that height of Maieſty or glory, though they may continew in a more obſcure manner. and be preſent, and perfectly perceiued for a very long tyme.</p>
               <p n="14">14. And you muſt obſerue that in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe viſions of our Sauiour, and his ſaints,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:34972:45"/>
you muſt haue a great reſpect vnto them, though they be from the Deuil, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke your ſpirituall profit of them; for you are not to hate, or contemne a ſweet pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, that repreſenteth one whom you deerely loue, becauſe it is made by a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inter of an euil life. but rather loue it, by reaſon it doth put you in mynd of your beloued, which is a comfort to your mynd. euen ſo, though the deuil being an excellent painter, should frame or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent in vs, the forme or image, of our Sauiour, or any Saints, we muſt not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect it, becauſe it is framed by him, but vſe it for our profit, with humility, and reuerence, for their ſakes whom we loue, and it doth repreſent.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Alſo you muſt not thinke them the holyeſt, that haue conſolations, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and reuelations; for many are great ſaints, that neuer had any of them; and others, that had viſions, and guſts, are not therefore ſaints, for true ſanctity, as I often ſaid, doth conſiſt in ſolid vertue, and true conformity of our will, to the will of God, in all things; but the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and guſts, are good, when they are from God, yet not to be affected, or deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and the beſt, and moſt ſecure way, is, to be indifferent, to be diſpoſed of, as
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:34972:46"/>
his diuine Maieſty shall thinke fitt, and eſteeme our ſelues vnworthy of any fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Our Holy Mother doth giue vs notice of other deceits, which are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to manie, that haue ſome degree of ſupernaturall prayer, and doe vſe great, and indiſcreet pennances, and thereby doe bring themſelues to great weakneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe; and of others, who by nature are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, tender, and weake; theſe ſoules fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in prayer thoſe guſts, and ouer io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yed with conſolations, and inward ſweetneſſe, doe languish, or rather through weakneſſe yeald, as one whoſe ſpirits, are decaying, and failing, and doe leaue themſelues in a manner dead, as if they were in a kind of rapt, by which, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is extreamly hurt, and more weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and they think it to be ſome effect of prayer, or the ſpirit of God, that doth worke ſo in them, and therefore they remaine in that manner for ſome houres to gether.</p>
               <p n="17">17. But they muſt reſiſt that weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and shake of that ſluggish diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for it is no other: and if that weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, doth proceede from too much au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, or pennance, by the aduiſe of their Ghoſtly Father, or directour, they
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:34972:46"/>
muſt eat, and drink, ſleepe, and recreat themſelues well, for ſome dayes, vntill they acquire ſtrength; for as is ſaid, indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet pennance, is hurtfull to body and ſoul; and if it doth proceede from the tenderneſſe, or weake conſtitution of nature, they muſt be more employed, in the actiue life, and outward things, then in the ſolitary, or contemplatiue life; for the very ſolitude, is able to make them weaker<hi>:</hi> and therefore, let them be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, being applyed to outward things, and let them be ſure, that this is very gratfull to God, and they no leſſe ſaints; for as I ſaid, ſanctity doth not conſiſt in contemplation, or hauing viſions, or ſuch like; but in true vertue, and confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, of our will, to the will of God;</p>
               <p n="18">18. So that if obedience command the actiue more, or rather then the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>platiue to be obſerued; we muſt be who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indifferent, and reſigned to embrace it with content; alſo euery complexion, is not fitt for ſolitude, contemplation, and much recollection; for ſome that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue themſelues to this, cannot goe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, nor profit, by reaſon of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition of nature, that would be ſaints, if they had applyed themſelues, to the charitable and humble workes, of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:34972:47"/>
actiue life; for though Martha gaue her ſelfe, to the practiſe, and exerciſe, of the actiue lyfe, yet she was a S. as well as her ſiſter Mary Magdalen, who gaue her ſelfe wholy to the contemplatiue.</p>
               <p n="19">19. So that they muſt in this caſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt that weakneſſe, and belieue for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that it is no effect of ſupernaturall prayer; for in this ſort of prayer, the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is rather comforted, and delighted, then troubled, or weakned; by reaſon the ouer great content, and ioy of the ſoul, doth redowne to the body, and it doth partake of her inward felicity, as it is knowen by experience, vnleſſe it be in the prayer of vnion, when the ſoul, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, and ſenſes, are wholy vnited, and drowned in Gods diuine eſſence, for though then the body be deſtitute, of all force, this doth not continue but for a short tyme (as I ſaid elſwhere) and it doth returne to it ſelfe againe, with ſtrength, content, and great ſatisfaction; and in that vnion, though the body be for a short tyme, as dead, yet the ſoul it more liuely inwardly with God; which in that other, she cannot be, but heauy, and dull; without any good effect, yea rather with many euil, and hurtfull, to body, and ſoul. Obſerue alſo, (if God
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:34972:47"/>
be pleaſed to giue you any of thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours, of Rapts, viſions Reuelations or other ſupernaturall things of that ſort) whether you be terrifyed or fearfull, at firſt, for commonly, if they be true, they worke that effect in the ſoul, though ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne after, she is in great quietnes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; moreouer you muſt not goe to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer through curioſity to know any thing by reuelation, nor adheare to your owne opinion, or proper iudgment, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any thing reuealed, but eaſily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the ſaying of your directour, or other learned men. Likewiſe marke, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be of vaine things, without any neceſſity, or profit to your ſelfe or others. and note, that whenſoeuer by viſions, words, or any ſuch, (which you haue in theſe degrees of ſupernatutall prayer) you find not your ſoul bettered in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; or that you perceiue in your ſelfe, any litle ſmoake of ſelfe intereſt, proper eſteeme, or vaine glory, make no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of them, but ſet them at naught, as falſe, and proceeding from Sathan; but the prayer, or viſion, bringing, humility with it, is to be much eſteemed, and God highly prayſed, with many thankes for it.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Deere Chriſtian ſoul, you may
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:34972:48"/>
read of theſe things more at large in the life of our Holy Mother, and in the boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes which she wrote, called, the caſtle of the ſoul, or the manſions, and the way of perfection. for I haue collected theſe thence; only that they, which God doth bring to theſe degrees or haue viſions, or reuelations, may vnderſtand, reading this litle treatiſe, what prayer they haue, and whether their viſions, be true, or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that they may not be troubled, or in continuall feare of being deceiued, by the deuil, as our Holy Mother was; which will be a great comfort to their mynd, and quietnes to their conſcience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>THE VII. CHAPTER. Of ſome obſeruations for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnderſtanding of what is ſaid concerning Prayer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHereas in the treatiſe of Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer there is often mention ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the ſenſitiue appetite, inferiour, and ſuperiour part of man, alſo of ſeuerall degrees of contemplation, (which I ſuppoſe are knowen to the learned) I thought good for the better ſatisfaction
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:34972:48"/>
of the ignorant, and vnlearned, to ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke ſomewhat of them in the concluſion of this worke. The ſenſitiue appetite, is a faculty conſiſting of two members; in the inferiour part of man; and hath its ſeat in the liuer and heart, or as others ſay, in the heart only, and it hath for its obiect, ſenſible good or euil, as it is appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by the imagination, as conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, or diſconuenient. the members or partes of it, are the concupiſcible, and iraſcible. The office of the concupiſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part, is, to incline to, and be moued to that which is good or agreable to it, and to decline, and shun that which is euil, or contrary to it; The office of the iraſcible part, is, to fight againſt the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultyes, which may occurre in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of the good, and shuning the euil; in theſe two, the eleauen paſſions, which are in man, are reſident, ſix in the concupiſcible, and fiue in the iraſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The paſſion is a motion of the ſenſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue part, which is moued by the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of ſome good, or euil, as conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, or diſconuenient, pleaſing or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to it. The paſſions of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcible are loue, deſyre, ioy or glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, hatred, flight, griefe or ſadneſſe. Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:34972:49"/>
is a propenſion of the appetite to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that which is apprehended as good; deſire or concupiſcence is a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe, or extenſion of loue to obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and embrace the good beloued; Ioy or gladneſſe is a motion of the appetite, reioycing in the poſſeſſion of the good preſent; for example, one ſeing a faire horſe, perceiues in him ſelfe an affection, or likeing to him, then deſyre, or concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence puts him on to cheapen, and buy the horſe, at laſt hauing bought him, and being in poſſeſſion of him, he feeles an inward ioy, and delectation, with which he is ſatisfied. Hatred is a diſpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence or abhoring that which is appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended to be euil or hurtfull. flight, is a turning, or going from it, ſadnes or griefe, is an affliction or oppreſſion for the euil that is preſent. as for example, one that is indebted knowing that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine officer hath a warrant to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend him, by chance doth ſee him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards him; at the firſt ſight of him, he is troubled, and doth find an horrour or diſlikeinge in himſelfe of it; then he deſyres to shune him, but if he be taken, he is daunted, afflicted, and his heart op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. and as the former paſſions, doe follow good, ſo theſe doe shun and flye euil.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:34972:49"/>
3. The paſſions of the iraſcible part, are hope, ſtoutneſſe, deſpaire, feare, and anger. Hope is a motion, or erection of the appetite towards the good which it apprehends may be had though with difficulty. Stoutneſſe is a motion of the appetite, by which it is encourraged againſt the oppoſit difficultyes which are imminent, and may hinder the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of the good hoped for; deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is a motion by which the appetite is afflicted and deiected; by reaſon it appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends that the good hoped for, through the difficultyes imminent cannot be obtayned, or had. Feare is an act of the appetite by which it is oppreſſed, with the apprehenſion of the future eiul, which it thinkes will happen; Anger is an act of the appetite by which is it mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to reuenge any iniury receiued.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And you muſt vnderſtand that the paſſions allwayes come's with ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of the body, chiefely of the heart, where all of them doe end. alſo you are to obſerue, that when we ſay the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite doth follow, or shun good, or euil, we doe not meane that, which is good or euil in it ſelfe only, but alſo which is apprehended, and preſented by the imagination, to be ſuch for often we doe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:34972:50"/>
imagine that to be good, which is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly euil; and that to be euil, which is good; as for example, one that is by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me accident greatly afflicted, and in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, thinkes it a great good to ridde himſelfe of that affliction, by ending his life with poyſon, as many doe, which is euil in it ſelfe;</p>
               <p n="5">5. Moreouer note that all theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, doe follow the knowledg that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede's from the ſenſes, and ſeekes after the three goods, which are in requeſt with the louers, of this world; and doe abhorre the contrary euiles; the firſt good, is that, which is called honeſt, that is, the eſteeme or honour of this world, the ſecond is that good, which is profita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, as riches wealth &amp;c, the third good is called delectable, as the pleaſures of this life. The contrary euiles are, Infancy or diſgrace, diſcommodity or want, grie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fe or ſadneſſe, which increaſeth in ſome to ſo great a height, through the heaui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe and dulneſſe of ſpirit, and the lan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guishing diſpoſition of the body, that they are vnfit to do any ſpirituall exer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciſe; ſo that ſuch as are inclined to me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lancoly are vnfitt for the ſtate wherein the exerciſe of mentall prayer, and ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues, is much vſed; for they are apt in oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſions
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:34972:50"/>
to fall into that euil. and obſerue that if the paſſions be ſweetly allured. and by reaſon, brought to follow vertue, which is truly good, they conduce to life euerlaſting; but if they follow their owne diſpoſitions, and wayes, they leade to endles damnation. which by the follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing example may appeere.</p>
               <p n="6">6. But for the better vnderſtanding of it, I will firſt shew what the inferiour and Superiour part, or portion of man is. for by that you may knowe when you doe follow vice or vertue, good, or euil. and as the Superiour and inferiour part doth proceede, the habits of vices, or vertues are acquired. The inferiour part of man, is the vnderſtanding, as it doth conſider, order, and direct his actions, and other things, according to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xims, and rules of the world, or created things. But it is commonly taken by ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall men for, the whole ſenſitiue part, with all its members, in as much, as it may obey the vnderſtanding and will. But as the vnderſtanding doth conſider eternall things and direct his actions and all thinge according to the law of God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is called the Superiour part, or portion of man. Now to the example. A religious man that is bound by his inſtitute to doe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:34972:51"/>
nothing without the licence of his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, being very thirſty, and hote, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the garden, doth find a faire ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fallen from a tree, looking at it, the ſenſitiue appetite is moued with a deſyre to eate that apple, then the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding diſcourſing according the law of nature, conceiues, that the eating of that apple is not only pleaſing, and delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but it is alſo profitable for his, health; for it will mitigate that heate, and quench his thirſt, and this conceit is propoſed to the will with thoſe circumſtances, all which is the worke of the inferiour part.</p>
               <p n="7">7. If then the vnderſtanding which is ordered according to the lawe of god, the will concurring, or permitting, which is the Superiour part, doe neglect to conſider that, to eate that apple is againſt the lawe of God, being a breach of his inſtitute, or if he doth take noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of it, and ſleighting it, giues a kind of tacite conſent, that the will may take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it, and ſo the apple is eaten, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hout licence; this conſent is a ſin, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, or veniall, according to the quality of the matter; as if it be in a matter of mortall ſin, it is mortall, if, of ſmall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, it is but veniall. this is called a lingering delight. But it is an expreſſ
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:34972:51"/>
conſent, when the vnderſtanding deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratly doth conſider it, and the will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to it, ſo conſidered; ſo that the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour part ought to ſuppreſſe that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of the appetite, and with contrary reaſons, to thoſe of the inferiour part, perſwade to omit the eating of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as being a ſin, deſeruing God's diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, the paines of hell, and the loſſe of the ioyes of heauen, for euer. Alſo it might ſay, alas, what a ſmall and tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory delight or content thou shalt haue in eating that apple, by which thou shalt looſe eternall ioy, and glory. or thus, (when the inferiour part is earneſt and the appetite much moued) my ſoul, did not our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus doe much for loue of thee, and wilt not thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare this litle for loue of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> perhaps for this one act, ouercoming thy ſelfe, he will confirme thee in grace for euer, and ſuch other like.</p>
               <p n="8">8. By this litle knowledg of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, you may the better regulat your ſelfe to diuine matters, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, or meditation, come to the contemplation of thoſe things which are eternall. for meditation is a diſcourſe of the vnderſtanding by which we labour to find out the truth of things; which
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:34972:52"/>
being found, the vnderſtanding doth reſt, beholding that truth with content, which is contemplation. In meditation, we are like a shippe at Sea, tending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards its port of hauen, through many dangers and croſſe winds. for there, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me's, one croſſe wynd, of an euil repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation, then, that, of an other diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then a tempeſt of ſome great temptation, then the heauy waues of the ſenſitiue appetites and paſſions (though not allwayes) giuing vs very litle reſt, but (as the shippe with contrary wynds, and ſwelling ſea's,) doe toſſe vs too and froe. thinke then what great labour muſt the Superiour part take in this caſe? the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore great dilligence, and art, is to be vſed, to get forward, and ſecure our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, that all difficultyes ouercome, we may reſt at length, in the hauen, of ſweet contemplation, (which is but a ſimple view, or beholding of the knowen truth, with content (for there, we are like a shippe at anker, and reſt, in the hauen, ſo long, and ſo much deſired, and wished for. by which you ſee, that meditation, is the high path way to contemplation, and without the long vſe and practiſe of it, that rich iewell of conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plation is not had</p>
               <p n="9">9. Contemplation thus deſcribed, hath
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:34972:52"/>
three degrees, the one naturall, the other ſupernaturall, the laſt diuine; by the firſt we contemplat God, as the authour and creatour of all things, and naturall veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, in them<hi>:</hi> as many philoſophers did; in the ſecond, by a ſupernall light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, we contemplat God, as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of grace, of whom we receiue ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall fauours and benefits; for we are borne the children of wrath, and by gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in baptiſme we are made the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God. and come to know the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of grace. by the third, which is diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, (as proceeding from the gift of the Holy Ghoſt, called wiſdome) we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templat God, and his diuine perfections; as that he is infinit, immenſe, eternall, goodneſſe it ſelfe &amp;c. to theſe three de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of contemplation, there are three appetites, or facultyes in vs correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. the ſenſitiue, the rationall, and the ſpirituall; by the firſt, we loue God, for our being as our creatour, by the ſecond. we affect him, for his many benefits of grace, as our chiefe benefactour; by the third, we loue him, for his diuine perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions only, as worthy of all loue for himſelfe; and according to theſe three, we may regulat all our actions, in this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe; of theſe that proceede according to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:34972:53"/>
the firſt S. Paul ſaid. The naturall man <note place="margin">1. <hi>Co. rinth.</hi> 2. <hi>v</hi> 14 <hi>Colloſ</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 5.</note> (that is, he that followeth ſenſuality) receiueth not the things of the ſpirit of God; of the ſecond, that tend to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian perfection, he ſayes. mortify your members, which are vppon the earth; of the third, it is ſaid by God to Abraham <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> walke before me, (that is in his Holy preſence) and be perfect, as Abraham, and Dauid did, who ſaid to God, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of my heart, is allwayes accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in thy ſight. for thoſe doe all things for the honour and glory of God.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Yet miſticall diuines doe ſpeake of an other degree of contemplation which they call, Sapientia vnitiua, an vniting wiſdome; and it doth conſiſt in the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the will, rather then in the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the vnderſtanding, for by ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogicall or ardent acts of loue, and diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aſpirations, the will inflamed, in a manner without the operation of the vnderſtanding, getteth out of it ſelfe, earneſtly endeauoring to be vnited, and to adheare actually to God. this is, of great perfection. But that diuine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of which I ſpoake formerly is an act of the vnderſtanding ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in admiration of eternall things, proceeding from the gift of wiſdome
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:34972:53"/>
with an inward guſt, and experimentall taſte of celeſtiall ſweetnes; for behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo many rare and ſtang things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; the vnderſtanding ſtands in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, this admiration cauſeth a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious attention, this attention bringeth a pure and very cleere knowledg of Eternall verityes, with ſo great inward guſt and ſweetnes, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding remaines wholy ſuſpended; hence diuine loue increaſeth, the ſoul is infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and knoweth not what to doe with her ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The effects of this diuine loue, are many, but thoſe principally, An extaſy, by which the ſoul ſeemeth to goe out of her ſelfe with ſeruour of ſpirit, to be transformed into her beloued; then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quefaction. which is a kind of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, or melting of the ſoul, that the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res all open, she might drawe her belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into her ſelfe as the ſpunge doth wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Vnion by which they are vnited, and doe touch each other. as we ſee two things ioyned together. mutuall inheſion by which hey now vnited, doe ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly embrace each other. Penetration, by which with cordiall affections she get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth within her beloued. Transforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by which she <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be changed,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:34972:54"/>
into the forme and perfections of her beloued. Zeale by which she doth ſo bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, that she can endure no Society of any in that good, which she doth poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe; theſe effects of loue are more forcibly produced when the thing beloued is in her poſſeſſion; but if her beloued be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, her deſyre to enioy him, is ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (and this is called feruour) that it doth procure an other effect of loue, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led languor; by which, (out of the exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue griefe and paine, which for his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence she doth conceiue,) she is often in danger to dye. for in deede it is able to procure a ſeparation of body and ſoul, and it doth happen to ſome. you may read of theſe things more at large in ſeuerall bookes, but chiefely in the booke written by the R. Fr. Iohn of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Maria, called the inſtruction of the nouices; and that which he wrote of ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and contemplation in the treatiſe of the paſſions; note that all the degrees of prayer and contemplation of which our Holy Mother ſpeakes, may be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to thoſe formerly mentioned. as the prayer of recollection, quiet prayer, ſleepe of the ſoul, vnion &amp;c. which are ſupernaturall, and haue contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:34972:54"/>
12. As for a rapt, it is a certaine eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by which the ſoul is exalted, by the ſpirit of God, to ſupernaturall things, with a kind of abſtraction from the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; you muſt obſerue heere, that a rapt doth include a violence which doth not conſiſt in that the ſoul is carryed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, by reaſon, that is agreable to her nature, but becauſe, she is with ſo great ſwiftnes carryed from the ſenſes by that abſtraction, yet the ſenſes as is formerly ſaid are not wholy loſt, vnles it be when the rapt is in the height, but they are much altered by reaſon of that ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and violent abſtraction of the ſoul from them, yet they doe well perceiue in that rapt (when the body is eleuated from the ground) that the body is in that height, which cauſeth great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the ſoul, ſo that the rapts proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe not conſiſt in the affectiue, but in the knowing powers. as when the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding with a kind of alienation from the ſenſes, or with ſome intellectuall vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is eleuated, and ſuddenly, ſnatcht away, or the phantaſy, or imaginatiue to ſome imaginary viſion.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The reaſon why rapts cannot be in the will, is, that the will is a kind of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion or inclination to that which is
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:34972:55"/>
good, and the more forcibly or violently it is drawen, the more conformable it is to his, inclination; for that cannot be ſaid, to ſuffer violence, which is moued according, to its naturall diſpoſition; but the more forcibly it is moued towards its obiect, the more delightfully it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. So that the rapts (by reaſon they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with violence againſt the naturall diſpoſition) cannot be in the will. yet the vehemency of the affection of the will, or ſenſitiue appetite, is often the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of rapts, when the ſoul doth very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibly adhere to thoſe things. which she doth affect, for by that force, she doth compell the knowing powers, to attend to the obiects, which she doth loue, as it were with a certaine violence drawing them from all other things. and the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue appetite doth the ſame. therefore they that naturally haue vehement incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations or affections, muſt diuert their mynd, to ſome other thing, when they find their deſyre inflamed, leaſt they be deceiued, thinking that to be from God, which is from nature, or the deuil; for if it be from God, though the ſoul endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to reſiſt it, all will be in vaine; for it will take effect;</p>
               <p n="14">14. Note, that in this, a rapt doth differ
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:34972:55"/>
from an extaſy, that an extaſy, is without violence, and therefore it is in the will, as is formerly ſaid, for it is but a going out of it ſelfe, by loue, to what it doth affect; and a rapt is allwayes with violence. alſo the calling, or inward touch of God, and certaine abſtractions by which his diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Maieſty doth forcibly drawe the ſoul vnto himſelfe as her Lord, are the cauſe of rapts; likewiſe by ſome light, or inward flame, alſo by ſome inſtillation of great ſweetnes, into the ſenſitiue ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, in like manner, by a kind of ſecret whiſtle, and many other vnknowen wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes, God doth efficaciouſly drawe the ſoul to himſelfe, by which, he doth giue her notice that he is abſolute Lord and creatour of all.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Moreouer, rapts doe produce other effects in the body, as its forces to faile, to wax cold, to fall into a kind of dead fit, to be eleuated from the earth, to hange in the ayre, to be very light and agill, as not hauing any weight. There are other rapts, which are not ſo forci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and are imperfect, by which. the ſoul is not ſo drawen from the ſenſes but she may ſpeake ſome words, and giue out he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any ſighs and grones, and ſomtymes the vehemency is ſuch that they caſt blood,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:34972:56"/>
and the body doth tremble and shake with ſtrang fits, and they do leape, runne and crye out by reaſon of the exceſſe of inward ioy. this is that celeſtiall or diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne drunknes of which I ſpoake before. To conclude, loue is the prime and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall paſſion, by which a man is drawen to all his operations; therefore S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine ſaid, my loue is my poiſe or weight, and whither ſoeuer I am carryed, thither I am carryed, to wit, where his loue is. For all the reſt of the paſſions doe follow loue, as for example. I deſyre to haue a thing, not for any other cauſe, but that I loue it; I doe not reioyce, or delight my ſelfe, but in that which I loue; alſo I doe not hate a thing but becauſe it is oppoſit, and contrary to what I loue; and therefo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re I doe flye and shim it. likewiſe I doe not hope or fight, but for what I loue, nor grieue, but for the euil which doth hinder me from what I loue, and ſo of the reſt;</p>
               <p n="16">16. He therefore that intend's to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire vertue, and the true loue of God, muſt heede carefully to what his loue doth tend, (whether to that which is truly good, and not apparent; or, to that which is according to the lawes of God, and not to the deſyres of nature; or to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:34972:56"/>
that which is truly vertuous, and not vicious,) and if he find, that it is not right, with ſweet perſuaſions, and ſolid reaſons, let him allwayes endeauour to reduce it, to piety, and thoſe things which are eternall; as if it be moued by the beauty of any creature; inſtantly, ſay, how farre more beautifull, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of all loue he, is, who made that beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, why then do'ſt not thou ſeeke after him who is eternall, rather then after this, which is to day, and gone to morrow. thy God is beauty it ſelfe, from whom all beauty is, he then is more worthy of thy loue, then this, which is, but a shadowe of what is loue worthy in him? O my ſweet ſoul, loue not that which brings thee to hell, but what may bring thee to heauen, and endles ioy. See, that what thou can'ſt loue moſt on earth, will faile thee, and decay, being but momentary, but if thou do'ſt loue God, thy ſweet and louing creatour, and redeemer, he will neuer faile thee, but bring, thee to enioy himſelfe in endles glory. thus ſweetly you muſt in all occaſions labour to induce your ſoul to the loue of God, and thoſe vertues which are contrary to your vicious inclination or loue.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Deere Chriſtian ſoul I wrote this
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:34972:57"/>
chapter for the better vnderſtanding of what is in the ſecond and third part of this booke, for there, it is ſaid, that you muſt mortify your paſſions; how can you mortify what you doe not know; for though you feele the paſſion, yet you know not what it is, or whence it is; which being knowen, with more eaſe you may mortify it, and preuent its ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling rage. and ſo by degrees going from vertue to vertue, from meditation, to contemplation, from contemplation, to a true transformation in God, you shall enioy, the begining of true felicity in this life, and compleatly in the other, which I moſt humbly beſeech God of his infinit goodneſſe to beſtow on thee and me. Amen.</p>
               <p>This booke is endend, to the honour and glory of God, and the moſt Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed V. Mary this 8. of September 1651. and if there be any thing in it, contrary to our Holy Faith, I doe moſt willingly ſubmit both it, and my ſelfe to the cenſure of the Holy Catholick Roman Church.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>By me, S. B. natiue of the citty of Dublin.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:34972:57"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF THE CHAPTERS, Of this Third Part of the Soul's Delight.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHap. 1. p. 1. A briefe relation of ſupernaturall prayer.</item>
               <item>Chap. 2. p. 19. Of Recollection and quiet prayer. more in particular.</item>
               <item>Chap. 3. p. 36. Of the ſleepe of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers.</item>
               <item>Chap. 4. p. 55. Of the prayer of vnion.</item>
               <item>Chap. 5. p. 62. Of Seuerall other ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations of the ſpirit, and how they differ from vnion.</item>
               <item>Chap. 6. p. 78. Of the manner of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpeeches, viſions, and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and how to diſcerne the true from the falſe.</item>
               <item>Chap. 7. p. 94. Of ſome obſeruations for the better vnderſtanding of what is, ſaid concerning prayer.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:34972:58"/>
            <head>Of the moſt marcable things contayned in this third Part. The firſt figure, will shew you the page, or ſyde of the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe. The ſecond, when it is. will deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the marginall Number, where that is to be had which is ſought for. and. this word ibid. Shewes that it is in the place laſtly cited.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ACquired vertues. what</cell>
                        <cell>p. 3. n. 2,</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Acquired prayer what.</cell>
                        <cell>p 4. n. 3.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Abbayes built in ſolitary places in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer tymes. and wherefore.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 6. n. 5.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Attention to diſcourſe, or inward words, doe hinder the benefit of quiet prayer.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 31. n. 11.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Abſence from God a heauy loade to a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſoul.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 66.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>B.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>THe Body doth participat of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ioy, in ſupernaturall prayer. the Body in vnion woyde of ſenſe.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 56. n. 2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>the Body eleuated aboue ground in rapts.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 63. n. 2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The true Body of Chriſt, is ſeene in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me viſions.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 85. n. 9.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:34972:58"/>
               <head>C.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>COnſolations not to be affected.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 29. n. 10.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Conſolations and comforts, which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes by diſcourſe, farre different from thoſe which God giueth in ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall prayer.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 31. n. 12.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Conſolations and comforts ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, doth recreat body and ſoul.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 32. n. 12.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>They giue health to the ſick.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 33. n. 13.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>diuine Communications are highly eſteemed by the ſoul.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 37. n. 2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Charity ordered in the ſoul.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 43. n. 8. &amp; p. 44. n. 10.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Chriſt more in loue with vs, then we with him.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 35.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The way to come to God.</cell>
                        <cell>ibid.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Concupiſcible part of man what.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 95. n. 1.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Contemplation what,</cell>
                        <cell>p. 102. &amp; p. 104. n. 10.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>D.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>DIſcourſe not, to be vſed, nor regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in quiet prayer, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 27. n. 9. &amp; p. 31. n. 11.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Death deſired; to be with God.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 74. n. 13.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Deſire. what.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 69.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>E.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>ELeuations of the ſpirit in prayer are many, yet diſtinct betwixt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:34972:59"/>
and from vnion.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 62. n. i.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Theyr difference is knowne by their ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 63. n. 2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Exraſis, haue their effects inward and out<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward.</cell>
                        <cell>ibidem.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Extaſy deſcribed.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 105. n. 11.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>F.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>FOrce not to be vſed in prayer, and why.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 89. n. 9.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Flight The paſſion. what.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 69. n. 2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Flight the rapt compared to a ſudden fyre.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 71. n. 10.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>G.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>GOds preſence ſupernaturall.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 4. n. 3. &amp; p. 10. n. 9. &amp; p. 24. n. 5.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>God and his Angells. where.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 7. n. 7.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>God doth worke recollection in vs.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 10. n. 8.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>God doth reward our labour in prayer.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 8. n. 7.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Guſts in prayer not to be deſyred, and why ſo?</cell>
                        <cell>p. 29. n. 10.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>God contayning all creatures in himſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, ſeene in a rapt and the ſins commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on earth.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 72. n. 11.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Ghoſtly Father to be acquainted with all viſions. &amp;c.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 87. n. 11.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>H.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>HVmility to be vſed in prayer.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 28. n. 9.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <pb facs="tcp:34972:59"/>
                     <row>
                        <cell>want of Humility in prayer very preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 29. n. 10.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>It is not want of Humility to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. that one is fauored by God,</cell>
                        <cell>p. 25. n. 7.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>It rather moueth to greater humility.</cell>
                        <cell>ib.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The benefit of a humble ſoul.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 33. n. 13.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Hatred what.</cell>
                        <cell>p<hi>:</hi> 96.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>They are not the holieſt that haue vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 89. n. 15.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>IMagination troubleſome in prayer.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 47. n. 17.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Very liuly in ſome.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 81. n. 5.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Infuſed vertue, what.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 3. n. 2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Infuſed prayer, what.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 4. n. 3.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Infuſed prayer is commonly giuen to mortifyed ſoules.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 5. n. 4.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Inferiour part of man what.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 99. n. 6.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Ioy what.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 96.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Ioy ſuſpendeth the ſenſes.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 74. n. 14.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>K.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>KNowledg clearer and purer in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry degree of rapts.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 66.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>L.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>LOue praiſed.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 47. n. 15.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Loue what.</cell>
                        <cell>p 95. n. 2.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Loue like a flame aſcendeth vpwards from the ſoul.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 66. n. 5.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The effects of diuine Loue.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 6. n. 8 &amp; p. 105. n. 11.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:34972:60"/>
                  <table>
                     <head>M.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>MArriage ſpirituall.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 58. n. 6.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Meditation what.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 101. n. 8.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Muſick often the cauſe of rapts.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 69. n. 7</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>N.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>NOyſe inwardly heard how it terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 68. n. 6.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>O.</head>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>OFfice of the concupiſcible and iraſcible part of man.</cell>
                        <cell>p. 95. n. 1.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>P.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>PRayer ſupernaturall. p. 4. n. 3. 4. VVhy doe not many profit, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue great fauours of God in prayer. p. 35. n. 15. Paſſion. what. p. 65. n. 3.</item>
                  <item>Power of God not to be reſiſted. p. 64. n. 3. The powers, for a long tyme after great rapts not themſelues. p. 70 n. 8.</item>
                  <item>Paine ſuſpendeth the powers in a certai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne rapt. p. 74. n. 14.</item>
                  <item>The Prayer that is allwayes after one manner is to be ſuſpected. p. 88. n. 18.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Q.</head>
               <p>QViet prayer. what. p. 13. n. 11. 13. &amp; p. 22. n. 4. In what doth it princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally conſiſt. p. 23. n. 5. Some are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, thinking they looſe their ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, when they doe not diſcourſe in quiet prayer. p. 26. n. 8. VVhat to doe in that prayer, if feruour be decaying
<pb facs="tcp:34972:60"/>
p. 28. n. 9. what the ſoul is to doe in that quietneſſe. p. 30. n. 10. 11. Other effects of quiet prayer. p. 34. n. 14.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>R.</head>
               <p>REcollection. what. p. 8. n. 7. 8. 10. &amp; p. 19. n. 1. More particularly &amp;. p. 22. n. 4. Rapts, with their effects. p. 17. n. 13. &amp; p. 62. n. 1. 2. 3. Specially. &amp;. p. 107. n. 12. More clearly. rapts are not in the affectiue but knowing po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers. ibid. n. 12. 13. Religious ſeeking after the things of the world, are like dogges returning to the vonit. p. 20. n. 2. 3. Revelations, viſions and ſpeaches intellectuall, and imaginary. p. 78. n. 1. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>S.</head>
               <p>SLeepe of the powers deſcribed. p. 13. n. 11. &amp; p. 41. n. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. to 16. Solitude fit for contemplation. p. 5. n. 4. 5. The deſcription of ſolitude. p. 7. n. 7. Spirituall ſolitude. p, 8. n. 7.</p>
               <p>Senſitiue appetite, what. p. 95. n. 1.</p>
               <p>Superiour part of man what. p. 99. n. 6.</p>
               <p>Supernaturall prayer the reward of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and ſolitude. p. 5. n. 4.</p>
               <p>Supernaturall prayer. ſee prayer.</p>
               <p>Spirituall drunknes. p. 43. n. 8. 9. to Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for God's ſake giueth great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to a ſoul in loue. p. 48. n. 15. Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſoules being vertuous, doe more
<pb facs="tcp:34972:61"/>
good in the Church, then many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. p. 61. n. 9. Sadnes what. p. 99. the Senſes not loſt in all rapts. p. 63. n. 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>T.</head>
               <p>THe Holy Trinity often ſeene in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall viſions. p. 64. n. 3. &amp; p. 71. 10. To be terrified at the firſt receauing of any great fauours, from God, a good ſigne. p. 93. 19. S. Tereſa, dyed of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, and not of any other ſicknes. p. 77. n. 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>VNion deſcribed. p. 14. n. 11. 12. &amp; p. 41. &amp; p. 55. n. 1. 2. Very cleerly. the effects of vnion great. p. 59. n. 6. 7. 8. The diuine eſſence doth penetrat the whole ſubſtance of the ſoul in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vnions. p. 58. n. 5. Vnion diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed from extaſyes, flights and rapts. p. 63. n. 2. Viſions, a ſpeciall ſort of them deſcribed. p. 71. n. 11. Viſions deuided into outward and inward, and theſe into Imaginary and intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall. 78. n. 1. 2. how to diſcerne when they proceede from God, or the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil. p. 88. n. 18. whether from God, or framed by our ſelues. p. 81. n. 5. p. 16. Thoſe without words deſcribed. p. 86. n. 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>W.</head>
               <p>THe will what. p. 107. n. 13. The whiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le of God p. 68. wiles of the deuil diſcouered, by certaine tokens and g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. p. 78. n 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8.</p>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:34972:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
